<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guidecard id="PITS.IT">
<?Pub CX edit5(guidecard(?>
  <?runhead left="Precedents — IP, IT, eCommerce and Media Suite"?>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,501" servnumber="272" startpg="yes" textcont="false"?>
<title>Precedents — IP, IT, eCommerce and Media — IT Bundle</title>
  <gc.front>
    <contents/>
<?Pub Caret 0?>
  </gc.front>
<comm.chap id="PITS.IT.AUTH">
<title>Author</title>
    <auth.info>
      <author>
	<auth.for>by</auth.for>
	<name>GORDON HUGHES</name>
	<?brk type="line"?>
<degree>LLB (Hons), LLM (Melb), PhD (Mon), FAAL</degree>
	<?brk type="line"?>
<position>Partner, Ashurst Australia, Melbourne</position>
      </author>
<author>
	<auth.for>The first issue of this title was prepared by</auth.for>
	<name>ANNA SHARPE</name>
	<?brk type="line"?>
<degree>LLM (Qld)</degree>
	<?brk type="line"?>
<position>Partner, Clayton Utz, Melbourne</position>
      </author>
<author>
	<auth.for>and</auth.for>
	<name>GORDON HUGHES</name>
	<?brk type="line"?>
<degree>LLB (Hons), LLM (Melb), PhD (Mon), FAAL</degree>
	<?brk type="line"?>
<position>Partner, Ashurst Australia, Melbourne</position>
      </author>
</auth.info>
</comm.chap>
<comm.chap id="PITS.IT.SCOPE">
<title>Scope of Title for Information Technology</title>
    <p>
      <ptext>This title INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY provides commentary on and precedents related to IT law, including:</ptext>
      <list>
	<li>
	  <ptext>key terms;</ptext>
	</li>
<li>
	  <ptext>an introduction to the main types of contract;</ptext>
	</li>
<li>
	  <ptext>implied contractual terms;</ptext>
	</li>
<li>
	  <ptext>intellectual property rights; and</ptext>
	</li>
<li>
	  <ptext>remedies.</ptext>
	</li>
</list>
</p>
<para.grp>
      <title>Forms and precedents</title>
      <p>
	<ptext>Amongst others, this title includes the following precedents:</ptext>
	<list>
	  <li>
	    <ptext>software licences;</ptext>
	  </li>
<li>
	    <ptext>software development agreements; and</ptext>
	  </li>
<li>
	    <ptext>an outsourcing agreement.</ptext>
	  </li>
</list>
</p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
      <title>Related titles</title>
      <p>
	<ptext>Commentary and precedents on related matters may be found within the following titles in the Australian Encyclopaedia of Forms and Precedents:</ptext>
	<list>
	  <li>
	    <ptext>
	      <xref xrefid="AEFP.ECOM6.C1" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com" link="y">eCommerce</xref>
	    </ptext>
	  </li>
<li>
	    <ptext>
	      <xref xrefid="AEFP.INI7.C1" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com" link="y">Intellectual Property</xref>
	    </ptext>
	  </li>
<li>
	    <ptext><xref xrefid="AEFP.MEDENT8.C1" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com" link="y">Media and Entertainment</xref>.</ptext>
	  </li>
</list>
</p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
      <title>Complementary titles in <wp emphasis="bi">Halsbury’s Laws of Australia</wp></title>
      <p>
	<list>
	  <li>
	    <ptext>
	      <xref xrefid="HLA_275" doc-code="HLA" link-to="com">Media and Communications</xref>
	    </ptext>
	  </li>
</list>
</p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
      <title>Index</title>
      <p>
	<ptext>Entries relating to this and other related titles are located in the Index to the encyclopaedia.</ptext>
      </p>
</para.grp>
</comm.chap>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,513" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<comm.chap id="PITS.IT.C1" comm-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)  " currdate="200711" currtype="review" group.style="2">
<title>Commentary to Information Technology</title>
    <?runhead right="Information Technology — 315"?>
<group>
      <title>Key terms in IT</title>
      <para0 id="PITS.IT.315-1" bw.pnum="[315-1]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Hardware</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Hardware is the mechanical equipment associated with data processing. It is sometimes simply referred to as “equipment”. Hardware comprises a central processing unit which interacts with input devices, storage devices and output
devices.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Common input devices are keyboards, mouses, scanners, cameras and joysticks; output devices include visual display units and printers.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Strictly speaking, operating manuals cannot be classified as hardware, although they have a utilitarian role.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-5" bw.pnum="[315-5]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Software</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The term “software” is generally used to describe a computer program. The term may also be used to describe associated documentation such as a user manual. In its narrow sense, software is not a tangible product but rather an intangible series
of instructions to the computer held on physical media such as in the form of silicon chips, magnetic tapes or disks. The media themselves are not classifiable as “software”.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Broadly speaking, there are two types of software — “systems software” and “applications software”. The term “systems software” is generally used to describe a silicon chip developed by the manufacturer which is permanently resident in
the central processing unit. “Applications software” refers to programs supplied independently which enable the computer to perform specific and varied tasks. Systems software should be distinguished from the “firmware”, which is the read-only memory
software controlling a computer between the time it is turned on and the time the primary operating system takes control of the machine.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>With all software, a distinction must be made between source code and object code. Source code is the language, not far removed from English, in which a program is initially written, while object code is essentially a series of electrical impulses
and is the “language” which the computer understands. Software is converted from source code to object code by means of a compiler program.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-10" bw.pnum="[315-10]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Multimedia</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The term “multimedia” loosely describes a product which uses more than one medium. It may incorporate text, graphics, animation, audio and video and is frequently interactive.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-15" bw.pnum="[315-15]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Internet</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The internet is essentially a decentralised, self-maintained telecommunications network made up of interlinking small networks. Associated with the internet is the World Wide Web, a forum consisting of billions of individual sites. The internet,
and its history, has been the subject of considerable judicial examination: see, for example, <case.cit>
	      <lit>Dow Jones &amp; Co Inc v Gutnick</lit>
	      <cit year="2002" volume="210" series="CLR" pgnumber="575" vsprefid="210-CLR-575" yr.encl="parens">(2002)
210 CLR 575</cit>
	      <cit year="2002" volume="194" series="ALR" pgnumber="433" vsprefid="194-ALR-433" yr.encl="parens">194 ALR 433</cit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2002-HCA-56">[2002] HCA 56</u.cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="HCA" bcnum="BC200207411">BC200207411</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
; <case.cit>
	      <lit>Macquarie Bank Ltd v Berg</lit>
	      <cit year="1999" series="ADefR" pgnumber="53[ndash ]035" vsprefid="1999-ADefR-53[ndash ]035" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1999) A Def R 53–035</cit>
	      <u.cit mncit="1999-NSWSC-526">[1999] NSWSC 526</u.cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="SC" bcnum="BC9902857">BC9902857</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 ; <case.cit>
	      <lit>Connect.Com.Au Pty Ltd v GoConnect Australia Pty Ltd</lit>
	      <cit year="2000" volume="178" series="ALR" pgnumber="348" vsprefid="2000-178-ALR-348" link="y" yr.encl="brackets">(2000)
178 ALR 348</cit>
	      <cit year="2000" volume="50" series="IPR" pgnumber="535" vsprefid="50-IPR-535" link="y" yr.encl="parens">50 IPR 535</cit>
	      <cit year="2000" series="FCA" pgnumber="1148" vsprefid="2000-FCA-1148" link="y" yr.encl="parens">[2000] FCA 1148</cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="FCA" bcnum="BC200004927">BC200004927</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-20" bw.pnum="[315-20]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Cloud computing</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Cloud computing involves using and storing data and programs on the internet in the form of a service, rather than via the computer’s own hard drive. The “cloud” simply refers to the internet and the infrastructure which underpins it.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Services typically delivered via the cloud include Software as a Service (SaaS) and Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS).  Services may include web hosting, data storage and webmail.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The primary attraction of cloud computing is that it enables users to acquire services as required and relatively free from concerns about the underpinning technology.  It enables users to minimise their investment in applications and infrastructure
and gives easy access to the latest technology.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Cloud computing has assumed considerable significance in the context of IT contracts, particularly out-sourcing contracts.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The challenge posed to IT contract drafting and negotiation is that the acquisition of cloud computing services may involve numerous service providers, not all of which will have a direct contractual relationship with the end user. This typically
needs to be addressed through a rigorous subcontracting regime.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Various legal issues potentially arise out of storage in the cloud.  Most typically, there are security, transborder data flow and privacy-related risks.  To some extent, these risks should not require the user to lower expectations of data
security or to assume greater risk, but, typically, service providers will express concern that they have less control over the choice of subcontractor or the destination of data as compared to non-cloud storage methods.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The issue has been the subject of review by various levels of government around Australia.  For the most part, Australian government bodies support the adoption of cloud technology where value for money can be demonstrated, but with the qualification
that normal security and other privacy standards must not be compromised.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-25" bw.pnum="[315-25]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>IT contracts</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>An IT contract is a contract for the supply of hardware or software or for services provided in connection with the selection, operation or use of hardware or software. Contracts of this nature may extend to multimedia, the development of web
sites and the delivery of software or services by means of the internet. For convenience, this chapter does not incorporate within the term “IT contracts” any online trading agreements and does not address some of the issues more broadly associated with
e-commerce.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
</group>
<group>
      <title>Contracting issues in IT</title>
      <para0 id="PITS.IT.315-30" bw.pnum="[315-30]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A number of issues are of particular relevance to IT contracts, even though for the most part they raise issues of general legal applicability. These include liability capping, proportionate liability and Personal Property Securities law.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-35" bw.pnum="[315-35]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Liability capping</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>It should be expected that virtually all IT contracts will incorporate a cap on the supplier's liability.  Suppliers will insist on it, principally on the rationale that the supplier has limited control over the extent of reliance which the
customer will place on a technology item or technology service. Customers often insist on a reciprocal cap, although this is more difficult to justify.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Liability capping has traditionally included a total exclusion of liability for consequential loss.  In the past, this expression was assumed to mean indirect loss falling under the second limb of <case.cit>
	      <lit>Hadley v Baxendale</lit>
	      <cit year="1854" volume="2" series="CLR" pgnumber="517" vsprefid="2-CLR-517" yr.encl="parens">(1854) 2 CLR 517</cit>
	      <cit year="1843" series="AllERRep" pgnumber="461" vsprefid="1843-AllERRep-461" yr.encl="brackets">[1843–60] All ER Rep 461</cit>
	      <cit year="1843" volume="2" series="WR" pgnumber="302" vsprefid="2-WR-302" yr.encl="brackets">2 WR 302</cit>
	      <cit year="1843" volume="156" series="ER" pgnumber="145" vsprefid="156-ER-145" yr.encl="brackets">156 ER 145</cit>
	    </case.cit>
, with parties typically
taking the liberty to deem certain forms of loss — such as lost profit and lost revenue — as falling within the definition even though, in some situations at least, such losses would more correctly be described as direct losses.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In any event, use of the expression “consequential loss” should now be treated with caution.  In <case.cit>
	      <lit>Environmental Systems Pty Ltd v Peerless Holdings Pty Ltd</lit>
	      <cit year="2008" volume="19" series="VR" pgnumber="358" vsprefid="19-VR-358" yr.encl="parens">(2008) 19 VR 358</cit>
	      <cit year="2008" volume="227" series="FLR" pgnumber="1" vsprefid="227-FLR-1" yr.encl="parens">(2008) 227 FLR 1</cit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2008-VSCA-26">[2008] VSCA 26</u.cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="VIC" bcnum="BC200800882">BC200800882</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
, the Victorian Court of Appeal overturned a decision by the trial judge to the effect that “consequential losses” are losses recoverable only under the second limb of Hadley v Baxendale. The trial judge had concluded that
certain costs incurred by the respondent were direct losses flowing naturally and directly from the appellant's failure to provide an adequately performing system and hence were not embraced by the appellant's contractual exclusion of liability for “liquidated
damages for consequential loss”. The Court of Appeal held, however, that the expression “consequential loss” should be construed as having its “ordinary and natural meaning” and that it was not correct to construe “consequential
loss” as limited to the second limb of <case.cit>
	      <s.lit>Hadley v Baxendale</s.lit>
	      <pop.case.cit>
		<lit>Hadley v Baxendale</lit>
		<cit year="1854" volume="2" series="CLR" pgnumber="517" vsprefid="2-CLR-517" yr.encl="parens">(1854) 2 CLR 517</cit>
		<cit year="1843" series="AllERRep" pgnumber="461" vsprefid="1843-AllERRep-461" yr.encl="brackets">[1843–60] All ER Rep 461</cit>
		<cit year="1843" volume="2" series="WR" pgnumber="302" vsprefid="2-WR-302" yr.encl="brackets">2 WR 302</cit>
		<cit year="1843" volume="156" series="ER" pgnumber="145" vsprefid="156-ER-145" yr.encl="brackets">156 ER 145</cit>
	      </pop.case.cit>
</case.cit>
. The immediate implications of the decision, if followed, are that suppliers may have broader protection than originally
thought if their contracts simply exclude liability for “consequential losses” and that this expression should embrace an exclusion of loss of profit, loss of revenue and similar losses. The decision in Peerless was subsequently cited with
approval by the New South Wales Court of Appeal in <case.cit>
	      <lit>Allianz Australia Insurance Ltd v Waterbrook at Yowie Bay Pty Ltd </lit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2009-NSWCA-224">[2009] NSWCA 224</u.cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="NSW" bcnum="BC200907207">BC200907207</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-40" bw.pnum="[315-40]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Proportionate liability</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Under proportionate liability legislation applicable in all states and territories, the liability of a defendant can be reduced to an amount reflecting that proportion of the loss or damage for which it was responsible. (In the absence of such
legislation, defendants would be liable on a joint and several basis, meaning that the plaintiff could claim 100% recovery from a single party, regardless of that party's responsibility proportionate to the other parties. This becomes a significant consideration
when addressing the liability of the respective parties).</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Contracting out</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>In New South Wales, Tasmania and Western Australia, parties are permitted to modify or contract out of the operation of the legislation: see Civil Liability Act 2002 (NSW), Civil Liability Act 2002 (Tas), Civil Liability Act 2002
(WA).</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>In the other states, contracting out is not permitted.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Typically, in those states which permit contracting out, the customer would prefer to exclude the application of proportional liability statutory rules so as to maximise its prospects of recovery in the event that it has cause to initiate action
against the supplier.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-45" bw.pnum="[315-45]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Personal property securities law</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>In drafting an IT contract, consideration should always be given to the possible implications of the <xref xrefid="OTH.PPSAC09" leg-code="PPSAC09" doc-code="OTH" link-to="leg" link="y">Personal Property Securities Act 2009</xref> (Cth) (PPSA).
 The background to the legislation and basic principles are discussed in the Personal Property Securities title of this encyclopaedia and also in the LexisNexis looseleaf service <emphasis>Personal Property Securities in Australia</emphasis>.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In the context of hardware sale agreements, retention of title clauses are no longer sufficient, on their own, to protect the interests of the vendor. For a discussion of the impact of the PPSA on retention of title clauses, refer to the Sale
of Goods title of this encyclopaedia. Where a hardware lease is concerned, the lessor's security interest in the equipment should be perfected by registering a financing statement on the PPS Register to avoid loss of priority and minimise the risk of
extinguishment of the lessor's interest.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Software licensors may wish to include a clause prohibiting the licensee from granting a security interest over the licence (a consideration relevant not only to simple licences but also to software development agreements where the developer
retains ownership of the software and licences it on to the customer). For further information relating to the granting of security interests over licences, refer to Chapter 4.9 of the LexisNexis looseleaf service <emphasis>Personal Property Securities
in Australia</emphasis>.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In escrow agreements, licensors and licensees may wish to seek a clause restraining the escrow agent from granting any security interests over deposited materiials.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The inclusion of a PPSA clause is not mandatory, and it will ultimately be a question of whether the supplier or the customer has the superior negotiating position.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
</group>
<group>
      <title>Types of IT contracts</title>
      <p>
	<ptext>The contracts discussed in this chapter can be summarised as follows:</ptext>
      </p>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-50" bw.pnum="[315-50]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Software licence agreements — Prr 315.1 and 315.2</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Software may be sold to a customer but it is generally licensed, as this enables the supplier to retain ownership and attach such conditions to the use of the software as it sees fit.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The licence agreement will set out the conditions on which the customer may retain the right to use the software — conditions relating, perhaps, to the specific equipment on which the software can be used, the right to make copies or
modifications, the rights of third parties to use the software and, as ownership is retained by the supplier, care and control of the media. A range of restrictions, largely driven by pricing considerations, may be stipulated by the supplier. The use
of software may, for example, be restricted to a maximum number of users, or to specific equipment or to specific customer sites. Such restrictions will obviously impact on the terms, and possibly the structure, of the contract. One such example is a
“multi-site licence”, an example of which is provided in this title (Pr 315.2), which enables the branch offices of a geographically dispersed corporate customer to order site licences by means of purchase order.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>It is important to ensure that restrictions imposed on the user do not purport to exclude or limit the operation of <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47B.3" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">s 47B(3)</xref> or <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47C" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">ss 47C</xref> , <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47D" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">47D</xref> , <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47E" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">47E</xref> or <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47F" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">47F</xref> of the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth). These provisions, embraced within Pt III <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.PT3.D4A" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Div 4A</xref> of the Act, provide users with a limited right to make back up copies of computer programs and to reproduce programs in order to make interoperable products,
correct errors and conduct security testing. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47H" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Section 47H</xref> states that a term in a contract which has the effect of excluding or limiting the operation of these
provisions has no effect.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>There are two clauses of particular importance to the user. First, the user should require an acceptance testing clause, setting out the criteria which the software must meet once installed before the licence fee is payable. Second, a user
should normally insist on an intellectual property rights indemnity clause to protect it in the event that a third party claims copyright in the software and alleges that the customer's use of the software is therefore an infringement of copyright.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The user's capacity to negotiate any terms at all will not exist where software is supplied, as it commonly is, by means of a “shrinkwrap” or “clickwrap” licence — these concepts are discussed at <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-70" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com">[315-70]</xref> and <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-75" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com">[315-75]</xref> below.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-55" bw.pnum="[315-55]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title>Webwrap licences</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Many websites contain terms and conditions governing the permissible use of material available on the site.  To the extent that these terms and conditions attract contractual force, they are known as “webwrap licences”.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Applying principles similar to those relevant to shrinkwrap licences <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-70" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com">[315-70]</xref> and clickwrap licences <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-75" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com">[315-75]</xref>,
the enforceability of webwrap licences is determined to some extent by the adequacy of notice which is provided by the website owner to the person accessing the site: </ptext>
	  <list>
	    <li>
	      <ptext>In <case.cit>
		  <lit>Ticketmaster Corp v Tickets.com Inc</lit>
		  <u.cit day="27" month="March" year="2000" jurisdiction="US" court="District Court" judge="Hupp J">(US District Court, Central District of California, Hupp J, 27 March 2000, unreported)</u.cit>
		</case.cit>
, the court expressed concern about website terms and conditions which were capable of being bypassed or which were obscurely placed.</ptext>
	    </li>
<li>
	      <ptext>	In <case.cit>
		  <lit>Pollstar v Gigmania Ltd</lit>
		  <cit year="2000" volume="170" series="FSupp2d" pgnumber="974" vsprefid="2000-170-FSupp2d-974" link="n">170 F Supp 2d 974 (2000)</cit>
		</case.cit>
, the court expressed some reservations regarding
terms and conditions which were obscurely printed on a linked webpage.</ptext>
	    </li>
<li>
	      <ptext>In <case.cit>
		  <lit>Specht v Netscape Communications Corp</lit>
		  <cit year="2001" volume="150" series="FSupp2d" pgnumber="585" vsprefid="2001-150-FSupp2d-585" link="n">150 F Supp 2d 585 (2001)</cit>
		</case.cit>
, webwrap conditions were held unenforceable
because they were bypassable and there was no evidence that the user had read them.</ptext>
	    </li>
</list>
</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>On the other hand, a user cannot draw comfort from a deliberate failure to read website terms and conditions which are known to exist: <case.cit>
	      <lit>Register.com Inc v Verio Inc </lit>
	      <cit year="2004" volume="356" series="F3d" pgnumber="393" vsprefid="2004-F3d-393" link="n">356 F 3d 393 (2004)</cit>
	    </case.cit>
. </ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-60" bw.pnum="[315-60]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title>Open-source licences</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Open-source software is source code provided free of charge on condition that the recipient undertakes to make the source code and any modifications available to third parties free of charge. An open-source licence is typically made available
over the internet and will stipulate that the product can be resupplied to third parties on condition that the third party accepts identical licence terms. This is not a sublicence — the end user will always enter into a licence agreement with
the original licensor, with copyright in modifications vesting in the original licensor in exchange for a perpetual licence back to the developer.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The rationale behind open-source licensing is that it provides the original copyright owner with a cost-efficient means of enhancing the product.  Some, in government especially, see it as a means of avoiding dependency on multinational commercial
suppliers.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>GNU General Public Licence (GPL)</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>The most common open-source licence is the GNU General Public Licence, more commonly known as the GPL. Although the commercial use of open-source software is a relatively recent phenomenon, the GPL was first published in 1989 and the current
version was published in 1991.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The validity of open-source licensing as a legitimate means of software licensing was upheld by a Federal Court in the US in <emphasis>Wallace v Free Software Foundation, Inc.</emphasis> (US District Court, Southern District of Indiana, Indianapolis
Division, 20 March 2006), with Tinder J concluding that the GPL in no way foreclosed other operating systems from entering the market but rather acted as a means by which certain software could be copied, modified and redistributed without
violating the software's copyright protection.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>In June 2007, the Free Software Foundation (FSF) released GPL Version 3.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,521" servnumber="272"?>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-65" bw.pnum="[315-65]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Software support agreements — Pr 315.5</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The concept of software maintenance is different to the concept of hardware maintenance. Software is not subject to mechanical failure. “Support” (or “maintenance”) in the context of software refers essentially to error
correction, but may extend to the provision of new releases, enhancements and upgraded documentation. A comprehensive description of the meaning of “support” in this context can be found in <case.cit>
	      <lit>GEACJ &amp; E Systems Ltd v Craig Erickson Systems
Inc</lit>
	      <cit year="1993" volume="26" series="IPR" pgnumber="643" vsprefid="1993-26-IPR-643" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1993) 26 IPR 643</cit>
	    </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In a software maintenance agreement, the crucial clauses will relate to the scope of maintenance services, the speed with which services are to be provided and the circumstances in which maintenance obligations will be excluded.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>It should be emphasised that in some instances, new releases and upgrades are the subject of the licence agreement, rather than the support agreement. This will be a matter for negotiation between the parties in each instance.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-70" bw.pnum="[315-70]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Shrinkwrap licences</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The term “shrinkwrap licence” refers to contractual software licence terms which form part of the packaging of a software product. Generally, shrinkwrap licences are printed on the outside of a package containing  the disks and are themselves
wrapped only in plastic wrapping. This enables the licence terms to be read without breaking open the packaging.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Shrinkwrap licences are used because the software proprietor rarely has the means, in a mass-market or dealer environment, to ensure the user signs the licence agreement at the point of sale. While the marketing practices of a prudent software
publisher will strive to ensure that dealers are properly trained and that end users are advised of, and agree to, limitations accompanying the rights to use the software product, shrinkwrap licences are sought as an additional form of protection. In
other words, they seek to deem the end user to have notice of, and be contractually bound by, limitations on its right to use the software product in the manner set out in the shrinkwrap licence terms.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Enforceability</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>The enforceability of shrinkwrap licences is a critical issue for proprietors of software packages which are either mass-marketed or which are sold through dealer networks.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>A degree of controversy has surrounded the enforceability of shrinkwrap licences. Essentially, the issue has been whether or not the licensee has in any given case been provided with adequate notice of the terms before the contractual process
is completed.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>There is no question that shrinkwrap licences per se are enforceable: see, for example, <case.cit>
		<lit>Dyason v Autodesk Inc</lit>
		<cit year="1990" volume="24" series="FCR" pgnumber="147" vsprefid="24-FCR-147" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1990)
24 FCR 147</cit>
		<cit year="1990" volume="96" series="ALR" pgnumber="57" vsprefid="1990-96-ALR-57" link="y">96 ALR 57</cit>
		<cit year="1990" volume="18" series="IPR" pgnumber="109" vsprefid="18-IPR-109" link="y" yr.encl="parens">18 IPR 109</cit>
	      </case.cit>
.
Whether, in a particular case, the licensee has been provided with adequate notice of the licence conditions is a matter to be determined according to well-established contractual principles: see, for example, <case.cit>
		<lit>Olley v Marlborough Court
Ltd</lit>
		<cit year="1949" volume="1" series="KB" pgnumber="532" vsprefid="1949-1-KB-532" link="n" yr.encl="brackets">[1949] 1 KB 532</cit>
		<cit year="1949" volume="1" series="AllER" pgnumber="127" vsprefid="1949-ALLER-127" yr.encl="brackets">[1949] 1
All ER 127</cit>
	      </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>In <case.cit>
		<lit>Step-Saver Data Systems Inc v Wyse Technology &amp; Software Link Inc</lit>
		<cit year="1991" volume="939" series="F" pgnumber="91" vsprefid="939-F-91" link="n" yr.encl="parens">939 F 2d 91 (1991)</cit>
	      </case.cit>
 , the terms
of a shrinkwrap licence were held to be inapplicable on the basis that the supply contract had been completed before the shrinkwrap terms had been brought to the user's attention. The case involved an allegation of breach of warranty by a dealer against
the copyright owner but the court held that the contractual terms crystallised when the plaintiff ordered the software from the defendant by telephone. A similar conclusion was reached in <case.cit>
		<lit>Arizona Retail Systems Inc v Software Link Inc</lit>
		<cit year="1993" volume="831" series="FSupp" pgnumber="759" vsprefid="831-FSupp-759" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1993) 831 F Supp 759 </cit>
	      </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The neatness of the approach in both <case.cit>
		<s.lit>Wyse</s.lit>
		<pop.case.cit>
		  <lit>Step-Saver Data Systems Inc v Wyse Technology</lit>
		  <cit year="1991" volume="939" series="F" pgnumber="91" vsprefid="939-F-91" link="n" yr.encl="parens">(1991)
939 F 2d 91</cit>
		</pop.case.cit>
</case.cit>
 and <case.cit>
		<s.lit>Arizona</s.lit>
		<pop.case.cit>
		  <lit>Arizona Retail Systems Inc v Software Link Inc</lit>
		  <cit year="1993" volume="831" series="FSupp" pgnumber="759" vsprefid="831-FSupp-759" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1993) 831 F Supp 759</cit>
		</pop.case.cit>
</case.cit>
 was disturbed to some degree in <case.cit>
		<lit>ProCD Inc v Zeidenberg</lit>
		<cit year="1996" volume="86" series="F" pgnumber="3d" vsprefid="86-F-3d" link="y" yr.encl="parens">86 F 3d 1447
(1996)</cit>
	      </case.cit>
 in which the court held that it was sufficient that the actual CD-Rom displayed a field before the database listing which warned the user that the software was subject to licence terms, even though the CD-Rom packaging itself
did not reveal the existence of such terms. This decision was subsequently rationalised on the basis that the parties had been engaged in negotiations previously and there was a mutual assumption that acceptance would be indicated by the customer's use
of the product, as opposed to payment: <case.cit>
		<lit>M A Mortenson Co Inc v Timberline Software Corp</lit>
		<u.cit day="1" month="February" year="1999" jurisdiction="Fed" court="Washington">(Washington Supreme Court, Court Appeals Division, 1 February
1999, unreported)</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Where supply through an intermediary is involved (assuming the intermediary is not an agent), there will be no privity of contract as between the copyright owner and the end user and neither of those parties will be in a position to enforce
contractual rights against the other. In such circumstances, the copyright owner will be deprived of rights in excess of those arising under the <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="n">Copyright Act 1968 (Cth)</xref> while
that party may still remain exposed to manufacturer's liability under the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) <xref xrefid="OTH.TPA74.PT5.D2A" leg-code="TPA74" link-to="leg" link="n">Pt V Div 2A</xref> and <xref xrefid="OTH.TPA74.PT5A" leg-code="TPA74" link-to="leg" link="n">Pt VA</xref> .</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Drafting considerations</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>No precedent for a shrinkwrap licence is offered in this title. Any shrinkwrap licence should, however, commence with a warning expressed in the following terms:</ptext>
	    <qpara>
	      <ptext>Warning: Permission to use this software is conditional upon the customer agreeing to the terms set out below. This sealed package should not be opened until all the terms of this licence have been read and have been accepted by the user.
By opening the package, the user will be deemed to have accepted the terms. If the user does not wish to accept these terms, the user must return the package unopened, whereupon the licence fee will be refunded.</ptext>
	    </qpara>
</p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-75" bw.pnum="[315-75]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title>Clickwrap licences</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A clickwrap licence is a software licence which is made available online, with users being required to indicate acceptance of the terms by clicking an “Accept” or “Agree” button before proceeding.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Enforceability</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>Issues applicable to notice and enforceability are similar to those discussed above in relation to clickwrap licences <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-75" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com">[315-70]</xref>.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext> In <case.cit>
		<lit>Williams v America Online Inc </lit>
		<u.cit day="8" month="February" year="2001" jurisdiction="US" court="Superior Court"> (Unreported, Superior Court, Massachusetts, No 00-0962, 8 February 2001) </u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
 the court
expressed reservations about an acceptance process which required users to choose between an “I Agree” or “Read Now” button and which, if the user selected “Read Now”, required a further choice between “OK, I
Agree” and “Read Now” (this second “Read Now” leading to the actual clickwrap terms). In other words, the court was of the view that the choice should, at least by the prevailing standards of the day, be uncomplicated and
unambiguous.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext> Subsequent decisions have, however, tended to assume a reasonable degree of sophistication on the part of the user — in <case.cit>
		<lit>Forrest v Verizon Communications Inc </lit>
		<cit year="2002" volume="805" series="A2d" pgnumber="1007" vsprefid="2002-A2d-1007" link="n">805 A 2d 1007 (2002)</cit>
	      </case.cit>
 , notice of clickwrap terms was deemed to be sufficient even though they were contained in a scroll box, and in <case.cit>
		<lit>DeJohn v TV Corp International </lit>
		<cit year="2003" volume="245" series="FSupp2d" pgnumber="913" vsprefid="2003-245-FSUPP2d-913" link="n">245 F Supp 2d 913 (2003) </cit>
	      </case.cit>
 , notice was deemed sufficient under a clickwrap licence even though it required the user to link to another site to actually
examine the terms.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Drafting considerations</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>A warning to the following effect should be included in all clickwrap licences:</ptext>
	    <qpara>
	      <ptext>Permission to use this software is conditional upon the user agreeing to the terms set out below. The software is offered to the user on condition that these terms are agreed and accepted. Acceptance will bind the user and the user's employees.
By clicking “I Accept” at the end of these terms and conditions, the user will be deemed to have accepted them.</ptext>
	    </qpara>
</p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-80" bw.pnum="[315-80]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title> Software trial agreements  — Prr 315.3 and 315.4</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Licences which enable the trialing of software come in a variety of forms.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>One form of trial agreement is a shareware licence, pursuant to which software is distributed for an evaluation period, at the end of which the user must pay a stipulated licence fee if the software is to be retained. Shareware is typically
distributed over the internet and hence the legal issues are similar to those involved with clickwrap licences <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-75" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com">[315-75]</xref>. The limits of shareware licences were analysed by the Federal
Court in <case.cit>
	      <lit>Trumpet Software Pty Ltd v OzEmail Pty Ltd</lit>
	      <cit year="1996" volume="34" series="IPR" pgnumber="481" vsprefid="34-IPR-481" yr.encl="parens">(1996) 34 IPR 481</cit>
	      <u.cit bcnum="BC9602953">BC9602953</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>While shareware terms are generally unilaterally imposed by the licensor, more formal trial agreements — such as software evaluation agreements or beta testing agreements — may be negotiated between the parties. A beta testing agreement,
for example, involves the testing of software “performed by users external to the company (most commonly, in the capacity of licensee or interim user) prior to the distribution of the software to the general public”: <case.cit>
	      <lit>Delrina Corp v Triolet
Systems Inc</lit>
	      <cit year="1993" volume="47" series="CPR3d" pgnumber="1" vsprefid="47-CPR3d-1" yr.encl="parens">(1993) 47 CPR (3d) 1</cit>
	    </case.cit>
. Under a beta testing agreement, the licensor expects formal feedback, in the form of reports, meetings
and perhaps prescribed testing over an agreed period, whereas the licensee will seek the option to retain the software for productive use if it is satisfied with the outcomes.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-85" bw.pnum="[315-85]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Software development agreements — Pr 315.10</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A software development contract is required when a customer engages a programmer to write a program specifically tailored to the customer's needs. Software of this nature is sometimes referred to as tailor-made software, bespoke software or
customised software.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Key drafting considerations</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>The two key issues to be addressed in such an agreement are:</ptext>
	    <list>
	      <li>
		<ptext>basis of payment; and</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>ownership of the final product.</ptext>
	      </li>
</list>
</p>
<p>
	    <ptext>With respect to payment, the developer may propose a period fee calculated on a time and material basis — the customer, however, may seek to protect itself by agreeing to payment only upon completion of pre-defined stages of development.
The absence of a clear agreement regarding title in the final product may have significant ramifications under intellectual property law and taxation law and should obviously be spelled out in the agreement.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>If title is to remain with the developer, then the agreement will incorporate a licence (perhaps on a perpetual or exclusive basis) for use by the customer.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Use of the customer’s resources</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>The other important aspect of a software development agreement relates to the use by the developer of the customer's resources — to what extent can the customer's personnel, computer equipment and other facilities be used in the course
of the project?</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>It is obviously crucial to clearly spell out the customer's specifications which describe what the customer expects the developed product to achieve in terms of functionality. Milestones and other obligations must be expressed with as much
clarity as possible: see, for example, <case.cit>
		<lit>GEC Marconi Systems Pty Ltd v BHP Information Technology Pty Ltd</lit>
		<cit year="2003" volume="128" series="FCR" pgnumber="1" vsprefid="128-FCR-1" yr.encl="parens">(2003) 128 FCR 1</cit>
		<u.cit mncit="2003-FCA-50">[2003] FCA 50</u.cit>
		<u.cit jurisdiction="FC" bcnum="BC200300200">BC200300200</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
. Sometimes, however, it is not possible for the customer's specifications and the technical specifications to be agreed and incorporated
into the contract at the time of signing. This will not necessarily invalidate the agreement, even though the parties are left with an unfortunate degree of uncertainty, so long as the contract adequately describes a process whereby this detail can subsequently
be determined: <case.cit>
		<lit>SVI Systems Pty Ltd v Best &amp; Less Pty Ltd</lit>
		<cit year="2001" volume="187" series="ALR" pgnumber="302" vsprefid="187-ALR-302" yr.encl="parens">(2001) 187 ALR 302</cit>
		<u.cit mncit="2001-FCA-279">[2001] FCA 279</u.cit>
		<u.cit jurisdiction="FC" bcnum="BC200101071">BC200101071</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-90" bw.pnum="[315-90]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Software escrow agreements agreements — Pr 315.15</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A corollary of some software licences is a software escrow agreement. It is not appropriate to discuss the concept of escrow generally in this chapter, other than to point out that a licensee may insist on the source code of the licensed software
being placed in escrow with a third party as it may be crucial for maintenance purposes. The customer may require this security to guard against the prospects of the source code being attached by the maintenance provider's creditors or being destroyed
by a natural disaster.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-95" bw.pnum="[315-95]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Equipment purchase agreements — Pr 315.20</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>As the title implies, an equipment purchase agreement is a contract for the purchase (and perhaps installation) of computer hardware. It should be noted from the outset that not all supply contracts include installation, particularly in the
case of microprocessors.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The contract will probably deal with such issues as whether operating manuals are to be included in the price, whether the equipment will be subject to pre-delivery testing and whether user training is to be included. Delivery and installation
obligations will be set out and this should extend to acceptance testing. As a rule, the equipment will not be deemed accepted (and the user will be under no obligation to pay the balance of the purchase price and the warranty period will not commence)
until the equipment has satisfied practical testing on live data which is sufficient to satisfy the customer that installation has been satisfactorily performed and the equipment is functioning as expected.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-100" bw.pnum="[315-100]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Equipment maintenance agreements — Pr 315.25</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Hardware maintenance may be incorporated in the equipment purchase agreement or it may form the subject of a separate agreement. The latter will obviously be the case where the supplier is not the maintenance provider.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Essentially, there are two types of maintenance. “Preventive maintenance” refers to routine checks designed to keep the equipment in satisfactory working order while “remedial maintenance” refers to services carried
out on request in order to remedy a specific fault.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Maintenance agreements will address such issues as the scheduling of preventive maintenance and the conditions under which remedial maintenance will be provided. The agreement may extend to such matters as spare parts availability, response
times, customer records, safe access and sub-contracting rights. The most contentious clause is probably the exclusion clause — maintenance may well be denied in circumstances where electrical or environmental adjustment is required, where damage
is the result of mismanagement of the hardware or where maintenance cannot be effected on site.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,527" servnumber="272"?>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.215-105" bw.pnum="[315-105]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Systems integration and software integration agreements — Prr 315.30 and 315.32</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Typically, a systems integration agreement will set out the obligations of the supplier in respect of delivery and installation of the system, and it will append agreements between the customer and any third parties involved in the transaction;
for example, if the supplier is the manufacturer of the equipment, but has no proprietary interest in the software, a software licence involving the customer and the software owner.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Systems integration agreements are sometimes described as “turnkey agreements” or “OEM (original equipment manufacturer) agreements”.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>A systems integration agreement will emphasise deadlines for delivery, installation and acceptance testing of the system. Such obligations will be independent of similar obligations relating to various components of the system which will arise
under the appended agreements. For example, acceptance testing of the equipment will be treated distinctly from acceptance testing of the system as a whole.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The most important aspect of a systems integration agreement is the acceptance testing clause. The principal responsibility of the supplier is to provide the customer with a system which works — it is fundamental, therefore, that the
supplier be required to ensure that the system as supplied is capable of performing as anticipated by the customer.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The other fundamental aspect of the systems integration agreement is a warranty of compatibility of components. This will involve reference not only to the customer's specifications, which will be appended to the contract, but also to applicable
standards.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>A related, although distinct, type of agreement is a “software integration agreement” (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-32" doc-code="PITS" link-to="oth" link="y">Pr 315.32</xref>). A software integration agreement involves the integration
of diverse software components in order to produce a new software solution. This is distinct from a “systems integration agreement” because the latter contemplates integration of both hardware and software in order to form a complete computer
system. Nevertheless the principles underpinning a software integration agreement are in many respects the same — in particular, the importance of ensuring that all software components interact and perform as an integrated solution in accordance
with the customer's specifications.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-110" bw.pnum="[315-110]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Service bureau and ASP agreements — Pr 315.35, 315.40 and 315.42</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A service bureau agreement involves an arrangement whereby an organisation (the service bureau) makes its computer facilities available for the use of another person. There are two ways this may be effected: either the customer can physically
transport its data to the computer site, have it processed and then collect the output or the customer can have direct access to the service bureau from a terminal situated on its own premises. Hence there are two types of service bureau contracts —
a batch agreement (involving, in effect, physical transportation of data to the computer site) and an online agreement (involving access by means of the customer's terminal).</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The key elements of a batch agreement involve the means of delivery of data to the bureau, the quality of the input information provided by the customer, the quality of the output, the time taken for processing and the means of delivery back
to the customer's premises.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In an online agreement, the important issues involve the basis on which the terminal or terminals will be, in effect, rented by the service bureau to the customer, obligations on the customer regarding care of the terminal, and maximum response
time criteria.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Both types of agreements will contain clauses concerning the consequences of failure of the bureau's computer, conversion of input data into an appropriate format and confidentiality regarding the nature of the customer's data.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Service bureau agreements are becoming less common and are being replaced by application service provider (ASP) agreements. An ASP agreement is a form of outsourcing akin to a service bureau online operation which involves the provision of
software and associated services by an “application service provider”. The ASP makes its software application available to a user, generally on a runtime charging basis. The advantage to users is that they can gain the benefits of the application on
a “pay for use” basis and hence avoid the full impact of licence fees. Typically, the ASP will make the application available over a network or internet connection.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-115" bw.pnum="[315-115]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Facilities management agreements — Pr 315.65</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>As service bureau arrangements have become less common, they have been superseded by facilities management arrangements. A facilities management agreement involves the management by one party (the supplier) of a computer system owned by another
party (the customer). Although such arrangements can take many forms, it is not uncommon for the customer to install its own hardware and software on the supplier's premises, and for the supplier to maintain the system and provide data processing facilities
to the customer.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In such an agreement, there will be quite predictable clauses regarding site inspection, installation of hardware, installation of software and commissioning of the system. Normally the agreement would not be deemed to commence until the system
had satisfied the specified acceptance tests and had, therefore, been fully commissioned. One important component of the system relates to third party software, being software not owned or presently licensed by the customer. In so far as additional programs
are needed in order to satisfy the customer's data processing needs, the agreement will have to address the responsibilities of each party in relation to procuring such licenses and complying with the terms of the third party licences.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The agreement will address issues such as support of the system (usually the responsibility of the supplier or a nominee of the supplier). Support would normally be provided by the supplier at no additional charge, as maintenance of the system
is generally regarded as fundamental to system management. As a corollary, the agreement will address system performance, with the schedule setting out minimum requirements in relation to response time and downtime. Excessive downtime normally results
in a rebate of fees to the customer, although this may not necessarily be the case in circumstances where the customer has provided the essential components of the system and the supplier expresses from the outset some reservations as to their suitability
for the customer's data processing requirements.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Another important aspect of facilities management agreements is the security provisions. The supplier will be required to keep both the data and the system itself free from unauthorised access. Sometimes only designated persons will be permitted
access to the system. As a corollary, a facilities management agreement should contain a comprehensive confidentiality clause.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Finally, rights on termination should be addressed. Normally, the supplier will be required to return the equipment in good condition upon termination of the agreement, and to return or destroy the software. An exception would occur in circumstances
where there were outstanding payments owing from the customer, this often being a trigger for early termination by the supplier in any event. In these cases, the supplier would seek to exercise a lien over the system.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-120" bw.pnum="[315-120]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Outsourcing agreements — Pr 315.73</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Service bureau agreements, ASP agreements and facilities management agreements are all forms of “outsourcing”. Nevertheless the term “outsourcing agreement” most commonly refers in industry parlance to an arrangement whereby the customer disposes
of its internal IT infrastructure and engages a service provider to run its data processing operations.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Drafting considerations</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>An IT outsourcing agreement essentially involves a commitment by the service provider to provide IT services which conform to prescribed service levels. This in turn gives rise to a number of performance monitoring issues which must be addressed
in the contract, such as:</ptext>
	    <list>
	      <li>
		<ptext>benchmarking (whereby the reasonableness of the service provider's costs are objectively assessed by a third party by reference to industry standards);</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>“technology refreshment” (whereby the service provider undertakes to upgrade the IT equipment on a rolling basis so that, at the end of the contract, the customer is not left with an obsolete system); and</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>“step in” (whereby the service provider agrees that the customer has the right to appoint a manager to oversee the service provider's operations where mismanagement is perceived as being the cause of deficient performance).</ptext>
	      </li>
</list>
</p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Outsourcing agreements of this nature will also deal with the process of “transition in” and “transition out”. “Transition in” involves the transfer by the customer to the service provider of relevant assets, third party contracts and personnel.
“Transition out” involves the reversion process, whereby management of the customer's infrastructure is transferred back to the customer or to a replacement service provider in a seamless and co-operative manner.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Outsourcing agreements also need to address the parties’ privacy obligations. A customer who is disclosing personal information to a service provider will seek to include clauses in the contract which protect any personal information which
is disclosed to the service provider. In these situations, both parties will have obligations to take reasonable steps to make individuals aware of certain facts. In particular, the customer will have to take reasonable steps to ensure that individuals
from whom it collects information are aware of the disclosure to the service provider. The Federal Privacy Commissioner has published an information sheet to assist service providers in meeting their obligations under the <xref xrefid="DAI.LEG.PA88" leg-code="PA88" doc-code="DAI" link-to="leg" link="y">Privacy Act 1988</xref> (Cth) in outsourcing situations.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The legal issues involved in an IT outsourcing agreement are potentially more complicated where “offshoring” is involved. “Offshoring” contemplates a situation in which the service provider's system, or personnel, is located in a country outside
Australia. The commercial attractions of offshoring come in the form of economies of scale and operational efficiency. Legal issues which need to be considered, however, relate to contract language, governing law, intellectual property protection, privacy
of transborder data flows and effective alternative dispute resolution mechanisms.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Depending on the complexity of the transaction, other challenging issues in contracting include:</ptext>
	    <list>
	      <li>
		<ptext>the prospect of multi-sourcing;</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>the likelihood of a cloud computing component;</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>governance challenges inherent in a multi-jurisdictional deal; and</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>audit and tax considerations.</ptext>
	      </li>
</list>
</p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-125" bw.pnum="[315-125]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title>Call centre agreements — Pr 315.74</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Call centre agreements, pursuant to which a service provider agrees to provide a facility to handle the customer's incoming telephone calls, are a form of outsourcing. While the public perception of a call centre is simply a group of people
answering a large volume of telephone calls, the operation is in fact a sophisticated IT exercise, and a call centre agreement will have to articulate the respective roles of the service provider in providing an appropriate IT environment and the customer
in providing an appropriate database of information required by the call takers in order to answer the incoming queries. A service level schedule will address the service provider's obligations in relation to call responsiveness, based in part on the
customer's estimates as to call volumes and distribution. Care should be taken to ensure compliance with the Do Not Call Register Act 2006 (Cth) which addresses the practise of telemarketing — <xref xrefid="OTH.DNCRA06.S12.1" leg-code="DNCRA06" doc-code="OTH" link="n">s 12(1)</xref> prohibits a person from entering into a contract with another person pursuant to which the other person undertakes to make telemarketing calls to numbers which are eligible to be entered on the Do Not Call
Register unless the contract expressly requires the other person to comply with the Act.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-130" bw.pnum="[315-130]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Non-disclosure (confidentiality) agreements — Pr 315.60</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The amount of time, money and expertise which frequently accompanies the development of a new computer product, be it a new program or an improved item of hardware, is by no means mirrored in the ease with which that computer product may be
copied or “cloned”. For manufacturers of software and hardware, this vulnerability of their technological innovations is often exacerbated by a high degree of mobility of personnel with appropriate expertise between different employers.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In the absence of any infringement of copyright by employees, it is often doubtful whether the technical knowledge exploited by them after the termination of their employment can be restrained on any legal basis. This is because the courts
will generally not restrain employees from exploiting the ordinary skill and experience they have gained in the course of their employment. It is only where the employee is seeking to disclose <emphasis type="ital" shading="nil">confidential</emphasis> information
that a remedy may be available to the ex-employer. However, rigid conditions have been developed before the law will recognise any obligation of confidentiality outside general contract law — the information must have been imparted in circumstances
of confidence and must be intrinsically confidential in nature.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>To overcome many of the difficulties associated with relying on general principles governing the law of confidential information, it is becoming increasingly more common for persons engaged in the computer industry to require their employees
to execute confidentiality, or non-disclosure, agreements either as part of the initial employment contract or during the employment (in which case the confidentiality obligation should be cast in a deed, unless supported by consideration). While such
agreements may require an employer to observe confidentiality obligations which would not be enforceable apart from contract, care should be taken that the obligations are not so onerous that they are invalid restraints on trade or open to attack on
the basis that they are harsh and unconscionable: see Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth) <xref xrefid="OTH.TPA74.S52A" leg-code="TPA74" link-to="leg" link="n">s 52A</xref>.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-135" bw.pnum="[315-135]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title>Privacy</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>“Confidentiality” and “privacy” are often addressed in the same clause of an IT contract but, while there are some overlaps, the two concepts are in fact quite distinct.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Whereas the laws of confidentiality relate to the protection of inherently secret information, the laws of privacy relate to the protection of inherently personal information which may or may not be already in the public domain.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Legislative regime</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>Privacy is regulated by the <xref xrefid="ACCL.CTH.PA88" leg-code="PA88" doc-code="ACCL" link-to="leg" link="y">Privacy Act 1988 (Cth)</xref> (<emphasis type="bold">Privacy Act</emphasis>). The legislation, which was initially limited in scope
to the regulation of the information handling practices of the Commonwealth public sector, has evolved over time and now regulates the private sector as well. The state public sector is subject to state-based privacy legislation.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Under the Privacy Act, personal information held by public sector agencies is protected by Information Privacy Principles and personal information held in the private sector is protected by National Privacy Principles.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The regulation of the private sector under the Act does not extend to employment records, small businesses with an annual turnover of less than $3 million, media organisations or political parties, and the transfer of information as between
related bodies corporate is also exempted from privacy constraints.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Radical reforms were enacted in 2013, taking effect for the most part in March 2014.  The most significant impact of the reforms involved the merger of the Information Privacy Principles (applicable to the public sector) and the National
Privacy Principles (applicable to the private sector) into a unified set of Australian Privacy Principles.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Privacy legislation has a particular impact upon IT outsourcing transactions, principally for two reasons. First, there is a question to be answered in each instance as to whether an entity has the express or implicit consent of the individual
to entrust the custody of, or access to, their personal information to a third party in the form of the outsourcing service provider.  Secondly, where the data is be stored overseas (or in the cloud, which may or may not be located in an overseas jurisdiction),
issues involving transborder data flows arise.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The contractual implications of the first issue — whether the individual consents to the involvement of a third-party service provider — are that service providers will understandably seek a warranty and indemnity from the customer
to the effect that the customer has the authority to grant the service provider access to the data in question.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The contractual implications of the second issue — involving overseas transfer of data — are that the customer will generally require a contractual undertaking from the service provider that it will handle the information in a manner
substantially consistent with the prevailing Australian privacy principles.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Issues peripherally related to privacy protection, and which may require specific attention in an IT contract depending on the circumstances, include the dissemination of “electronic junk mail” which is governed by the Spam Act 2003 (Cth),
and the use of spyware which, while not directly the subject of legislation, falls within the scope of legislation such as the Workplace Surveillance Act 2005 (NSW).</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<?Pub _bookmark Command="13 Feb 2006"?>
      </para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-140" bw.pnum="[315-140]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Consultancy agreements — Pr 315.45</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>There is a variety of circumstances in which participants in the computer industry require consultancy agreements. For example, a consultant may be needed for a short term to develop a computer program or to advise on or assist in the acquisition
or installation of a computer system. The nature of contractual obligations will depend on the nature of the consultancy services to be furnished, but among the issues which should invariably be addressed are those relating to confidentiality, ownership
of intellectual property, duration of the engagement and the services to be provided.</ptext>
	</p>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,537" servnumber="272"?>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-145" bw.pnum="[315-145]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Backup agreements — Prr 315.50, 315.75</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Use of a computer system does not always engage the full capacity of the system. In these circumstances, there may be several users having similar systems that are able to provide mutual backup if the system of one of them “crashes”.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Agreements governing such mutual backup should carefully define such matters as the events which trigger a backup obligation, the available capacities of both parties’ systems, the circumstances in which a party may be excepted from the obligation
to provide system backup, the personnel requirements of both parties and the obligations of the party making use of the other's system.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Needless to say, confidentiality obligations are of paramount importance in this type of agreement.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp level="1">
	  <title>IT analysis agreements Prr 315.76, 315.77, 315.78. 315.79</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>It is often necessary to develop an IT contract for a relatively esoteric, project-specific activity. In many respects, these are a hybrid of general consultancy agreements <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-140" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com" link="y">[315-140]</xref> although they can assume a unique form of industry terminology and approach. A number of examples are given in this text.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>An enterprise architecture analysis agreement, for example, involves an assessment of an organisation's business objectives, with particular emphasis on its supporting IT environment, and requires the consultant to provide a report on the suitability
of the customer's existing processes and the potential for achieving greater efficiencies through a rationalisation or redesign of the supporting technology.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>A gap analysis agreement (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-75" doc-code="PITS" link-to="oth" link="y">Pr 315.75</xref>) involves an assessment of the discrepancy between a customer's requirements as set out in a request for tender, and the
functionality offered by the preferred tenderer in its response. The discrepancy represents the “gap” and the consultant is required to assess the significance of the discrepancy and to determine the technical and practical implications.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>An implementation planning study agreement (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-76" doc-code="PITS" link-to="oth" link="y">Pr 315.76</xref>) is often conducted by a supplier prior to the rollout of system implementation services with a view
to assessing the customer's implementation requirements and identifying any issues which may be encountered in the process. </ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>A scoping agreement (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-77" doc-code="PITS" link-to="oth" link="y">Pr 315.77</xref>) is in many respects similar to an implementation planning study agreement, and involves an analysis of the level of resources
which a supplier estimates it will require in order to identify with some precision the scope of an impending project and to produce preliminary material such as technical specifications, time estimates and precise costings. </ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp level="1">
	  <title>Security agreements — Prr 315.78, 315.79</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>A system access agreement (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-78" doc-code="PITS" link-to="oth" link="y">Pr 315.78</xref>) permits an authorised user to have access to the customer's system for a specific, identified purpose.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>A penetration testing agreement (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-79" doc-code="PITS" link-to="oth" link="y">Pr 315.79</xref>) is similar in many respects to a system access agreement, save that the specific objective of the service provider
is to identify any security shortcomings which might otherwise enable an unauthorised third party to hack into the customer's system.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-150" bw.pnum="[315-150]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Guarantees of performance — Pr 315.55</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Users may place a great deal of reliance on their computer system for the efficient and profitable conduct of their business. The existence of tightly drafted exclusion clauses, doubts surrounding the financial situation of the system supplier
or the fact that the supplier is a distributor of the product only are all matters which may prompt the user to seek a guarantee of the performance of the supplier's obligations. An escrow agreement is one such form of security. A deed of guarantee of
performance is another.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The user may require the deed to be executed by a variety of persons interested in the supply of the computer product or computer-related services in question, including directors of the supplier company, the parent company of the supplier
or the manufacturer of the product.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-155" bw.pnum="[315-155]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Panel agreements — Pr 315.80</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Customers involved in large scale IT procurement may establish a panel of pre-qualified suppliers from which the customer can choose to make a purchase.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Panel agreements are essentially the same as other IT contracts (for example, a panel agreement for the supply of computer hardware will contain many of the same provisions as a common equipment purchase contract) but will also include provisions
dealing with panel membership.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Typically, a panel contract will specify the duration of the term of appointment to the panel and reserve the right of the customer to utilise non-panel members, at least in extenuating circumstances. Normally a customer would seek to include
a provision to the effect that no minimum number of orders is guaranteed. For its part, the supplier will be required to undertake to make its products or services available on agreed terms for the duration of its panel membership. The agreement will
also stipulate an ordering procedure to be utilised when a customer seeks to engage a particular panel member.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-160" bw.pnum="[315-160]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Term agreement — Pr 315.85</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A customer with ongoing procurement requirements may appoint a supplier for a specified term. For example, a specified supplier might be given the exclusive right to meet the customer's equipment requirements for a period of two years, subject
to the placement of orders by the customer from time to time.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Term agreements will for the most part look the same as traditional IT contracts but they will include provisions specific to the ongoing nature of the relationship. For example, the duration of the arrangement will be specified, and the supplier
will undertake to make the specified products or services available on agreed terms during that period. An ordering procedure will also be set out in the contract.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-165" bw.pnum="[315-165]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Internet service provider agreement — Pr 315.90</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>To access the internet, most users require a contract with an internet service provider (ISP).  An ISP provides access to the  internet through its own computer system. An agreement between an ISP and a user is known as an “ISP agreement”.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Typically, an ISP agreement will state that the ISP's principal obligation is to provide the customer with all identification and login information, while the customer will be responsible for providing, computer hardware, software and other
equipment necessary to access the service.  The customer will undertake to use its access rights for lawful purposes and the agreement will expressly absolve the ISP from responsibility for supervision, editing or control of the content of information.
An ISP agreement may incorporate, directly or by reference, an “acceptable use policy” which sets out the ISP's ethical approach to internet usage.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-170" bw.pnum="[315-170]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Website and portal development agreements — Pr 315.95</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A website development agreement sets out the terms on which the service provider is engaged to develop a website for a customer.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>There are many similarities in the structuring of software development and website development agreements, although a website development agreement will generally concentrate to a greater extent on the level of customer responsibility. Typically,
the agreement will specify that the customer is responsible for providing the developer with all relevant data and other material which it specifically seeks to have incorporated into the website, while the developer will seek a disclaimer in relation
to any inadequacy in the website which results from a failure by the customer to provide adequate cooperation or input.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>A portal is a website which enables the user to utilise external links to other websites, indexed by key words and topics. Structurally, a portal development agreement is similar to a website development agreement.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-175" bw.pnum="[315-175]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Teaming agreements — Pr 315.100</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>“Teaming” is a loosely used expression which can mean a number of things within the IT industry. From a contractual perspective, it can apply to anything from consultancy to outsourcing to distributorship. Most commonly, however, “teaming”
refers to a collaborative approach between two parties (perhaps with distinct but interrelated skills) in respect of a specific project.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>This chapter includes a sample “teaming agreement” but again it must be stressed that in every instance, much will depend on the precise requirements of the parties. The looseness of the use of the term, and the legal pitfalls associated with
ill-defined “teaming” arrangements, were the subject of comment by the Federal Court in <case.cit>
	      <lit>BNWP Enterprises Pty Ltd v Unisys Australia Ltd</lit>
	      <u.cit mncit="1997-FCA-1">[1997] FCA 1</u.cit>
	      <u.cit bcnum="BC9700744">BC9700744</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-180" bw.pnum="[315-180]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Multimedia development agreements — Pr 315.105</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Multimedia development agreements involve the engagement of a supplier to develop a multimedia product to the customer's specifications.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In many respects, the legal issues are similar to those involved in software development agreement, but particular attention needs to be paid to the ownership of intellectual property rights. Because diverse protected works (particularly artistic
and musical) might be incorporated into a product, it is essential to ensure that permission is obtained from the relevant owners of intellectual property rights in each and every component. In turn it becomes important to clarify precisely what level
of ownership will be assigned to the customer and to what extent ownership of component parts will remain vested in third parties.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Intellectual property issues have troubled Australian courts in the past. In <case.cit>
	      <lit>Galaxy Electronics Pty Ltd v Sega Enterprises Ltd</lit>
	      <cit year="1997" volume="75" series="FCR" pgnumber="8" vsprefid="75-FCR-8" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1997) 75 FCR 8</cit>
	      <cit year="1997" volume="145" series="ALR" pgnumber="21" vsprefid="145-ALR-21" link="n" yr.encl="parens">145 ALR 21</cit>
	      <cit>37 IPR 462</cit>
	      <u.cit year="1997"> BC9702028</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 , the Full Court of the Federal Court
concluded that a multimedia product in the form of a video game was classifiable as a “cinematograph film”, as did Sackville J in <case.cit>
	      <lit>Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment v Stevens</lit>
	      <cit year="2002" volume="200" series="ALR" pgnumber="55" vsprefid="2002-200-ALR-55" link="y">(2002) 200 ALR 55</cit>
	      <cit year="2002" volume="55" series="IPR" pgnumber="497" vsprefid="55-IPR-497" link="y" yr.encl="parens">55 IPR 497</cit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2002-FCA-906">[2002] FCA 906</u.cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="Fed" bcnum="BC200204129"> BC200204129</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 . A different conclusion was reached, on the facts, by the Full Court of the Federal Court in <case.cit>
	      <lit>Pacific Gaming Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Leisure Industries Pty Ltd</lit>
	      <cit year="2001" volume="116" series="FCR" pgnumber="448" vsprefid="116-FCR-448" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(2001) 116 FCR 448</cit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2001-FCA-1636"> [2001] FCA 1636</u.cit>
	      <u.cit bcnum="BC200107323"> BC200107323</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-185" bw.pnum="[315-185]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Government contracts (including GITC)</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>In July 1991, the Commonwealth and state governments adopted a common IT contracting template, known as the Government Information Technology Conditions (GITC), which continue to form the basis of IT transactions in a number of jurisdictions.
This involves a pro forma modular approach, comprising both boilerplate terms and a series of optional modules (embracing the supply of hardware and software and the provision of a range of services) which can be selected and implemented in accordance
with the requirements of the transaction in question.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The original GITC was replaced from 1 December 1994 with GITC version 2. Generally, versions 1 and 2 are regarded as pro-government and are designed to maximise the government's buying power by imposing on the supplier mandatory conditions
which strongly favour the customer.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>There was a deviation in this approach in October 1998 when GITC version 3 was published. This was a more even-handed approach and involved pro forma terms and conditions negotiated by government representatives with the Australian Information
Industry Association. Not all Australian jurisdictions agreed to adopt this version, however, some preferring to remain with GITC version 2 on the basis that it was more favourable to government, even though it was perceived by some buyers as being unduly
long and complex for small transactions and by some suppliers as being unduly weighted in favour of buyers.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>GITC 3 was superseded at the Commonwealth level by GITC version 4 on 3 August 2001. By the end of the 2002, GITC version 4 had also been adopted in Victoria, Western Australia and the Australian Capital Territory, with other jurisdictions
preferring to remain with GITC version 2.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>By the end of 2004, a GITC version 5 had emerged in Queensland, while New South Wales had moved away from GITC altogether and was phasing in its own IT contract template known as “Procure IT”.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In May 2006, the Commonwealth Department of Finance and Administration published a revised IT contract template under the title “Source IT”. The first suite of contracts covered IT consultancy, hardware acquisition and support and
commercial off-the-shelf software licence acquisition and support. Version 2.3 was released in October 2012.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
</group>
<group>
      <?fascicle nextpg="12,545" servnumber="272"?>
<title>Consumer guarantees</title>
      <para0 id="PITS.IT.315-190" bw.pnum="[315-190]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>The Australian Consumer Law</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The Competition and Consumer Act 2010 (Cth) contains a number of rules that businesses must abide by in their dealings with consumers. These rules are collectively known as the Australian Consumer Law (<emphasis type="bold">ACL</emphasis>).</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The ACL brings together a number of national, state and territory laws and is enforced by the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission and state and territory consumer protection agencies.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The relevant portion of the ACL for the purpose of this discussion is Pt III-II, Div 1 which relates to “consumer guarantees”.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Key terms</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>“Goods” is given an inclusive definition (see s 2 of the ACL). It can be assumed that “goods” will include, prima facie, all computer hardware and peripherals unless the hardware is classifiable as a fixture.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>“Services” includes “any rights … benefits, privileges or facilities that are or are to be, provided, granted or conferred in trade or commerce” and is specifically extended to contracts for the performance of
work, whether with or without the supply of goods: s 2 of the ACL.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>“Consumer” is, in many respects, the key definition. Where the supply of goods is concerned, a person will be classified as a “consumer” only if the price of goods does not exceed $40,000 (s 3(1) of the ACL) or,
where the price exceeds $40,000, the goods are of a kind ordinarily acquired for personal, domestic or household use or consumption. In either case, the person will not be a “consumer” if the goods were acquired, or the person held himself
or herself out as acquiring the goods, for the purpose of re-supply or for the purpose of using them up or transforming them, in trade or commerce, in the course of a process of production or manufacture or of repairing or treating other goods or fixtures
on land. Where the supply of services is concerned, a person will only be regarded as a “consumer” if the price of the services does not exceed $40,000 or, if this price is exceeded, the services were of a kind ordinarily acquired for personal,
domestic or household use or consumption: s 3(3) of the ACL. It may be concluded, therefore, that the Act would not extend to situations where a distributor, for example, buys goods from the manufacturer for the purpose of re-supply or where a maintenance
company purchases spare parts from a third party in order to repair or treat hardware.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Consumer guarantees</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>The ACL may operate to impose consumer guarantees into contracts for the sale, lease, installation and maintenance of hardware, unless that hardware constitutes a fixture. It may also imply terms into contracts for the sale, licensing, development,
maintenance and perhaps distribution of software.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The key guarantees include guarantees as to:</ptext>
	    <list>
	      <li>
		<ptext>title (s 51);</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>undisturbed possession (s 52);</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>undisclosed securities (s 53);</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>acceptable quality (s 54);</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>fitness for purpose (s 55);</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>correspondence with the description (s 56); and</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>correspondence with sample (s 57).</ptext>
	      </li>
</list>
</p>
<p>
	    <ptext>With respect to services, there are guarantees:</ptext>
	    <list>
	      <li>
		<ptext>that services will be provided with due care and skill (s 60);</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>of fitness for purpose (s 61); and</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>of a reasonable time for supply (s 62).</ptext>
	      </li>
</list>
</p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>No contracting out</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>Consumer guarantees cannot be excluded but can be limited to the extent specified in s 64A. Such a limitation will not be effective, however, if the consumer can establish that it was not fair or reasonable for the supplier to rely on
that term of the contract.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-195" bw.pnum="[315-195]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title>Remedies relating to guarantees</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>See Div 1 of Pt 5-4 of the Australian Consumer Law (<emphasis type="bold">ACL</emphasis>). To a large extent, a consumer's options are determined by the nature of the problem — whether it is a “major failure” or a “minor failure”.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Subsections (1), (2) and (3) of s 259 provide:</ptext>
	  <repro.leg>
	    <r.subsect>
	      <label>(1)</label>
	      <lp.txt>A consumer may take action under this section if:</lp.txt>
	      <r.subpara1>
		<label>(a)</label>
		<lp.txt>a person (the supplier) supplies, in trade or commerce, goods to the consumer; and</lp.txt>
	      </r.subpara1>
<r.subpara1>
		<label>(b)</label>
		<lp.txt>a guarantee that applies to the supply under Subdivision A of Division 1 of Part 3-2 (other than sections 58 and 59(1)) is not complied with.</lp.txt>
	      </r.subpara1>
</r.subsect>
<r.subsect>
	      <label>(2)</label>
	      <lp.txt>If the failure to comply with the guarantee can be remedied and is not a major failure:</lp.txt>
	      <r.subpara1>
		<label>(a)</label>
		<lp.txt>the consumer may require the supplier to remedy the failure within a reasonable time; or</lp.txt>
	      </r.subpara1>
<r.subpara1>
		<label>(b)</label>
		<lp.txt>if such a requirement is made of the supplier but the supplier refuses or fails to comply with the requirement, or fails to comply with the requirement within a reasonable time — the consumer may:</lp.txt>
		<r.subpara2>
		  <label>(i)</label>
		  <lp.txt>otherwise have the failure remedied and, by action against the supplier, recover all reasonable costs incurred by the consumer in having the failure so remedied; or </lp.txt>
		</r.subpara2>
<r.subpara2>
		  <label>(ii)</label>
		  <lp.txt>subject to section 262, notify the supplier that the consumer rejects the goods and of the ground or grounds for the rejection.</lp.txt>
		</r.subpara2>
</r.subpara1>
</r.subsect>
<r.subsect>
	      <label>(3)</label>
	      <lp.txt>If the failure to comply with the guarantee cannot be remedied or is a major failure, the consumer may:</lp.txt>
	      <r.subpara1>
		<label>(a)</label>
		<lp.txt>subject to section 262, notify the supplier that the consumer rejects the goods and of the ground or grounds for the rejection; or</lp.txt>
	      </r.subpara1>
<r.subpara1>
		<label>(b)</label>
		<lp.txt>by action against the supplier, recover compensation for any reduction in the value of the goods below the price paid or payable by the consumer for the goods.</lp.txt>
	      </r.subpara1>
</r.subsect>
</repro.leg>
</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In short, where the problem is minor, the consumer may seek to have the fault rectified but the supplier may, as an alternative, offer a replacement or a refund; and in the case of a “major failure”, the consumer may opt for a refund or replacement
or retain the goods and seek compensation for any reduction in value.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>In this context, a “major failure” in the context of goods is defined in s 260. A “major failure” in the context of services is defined in s 268.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Division 2 of Pt 5-4 of the ACL provides consumers with the ability to enforce a remedy against a manufacturer in certain circumstances.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Section 271 provides that if there is a failure to comply with the guarantee as to acceptable quality set out in s 54, an affected person may recover damages from the manufacturer, subject to various exceptions. A refusal or failure by
the manufacturer to remedy the problem within a reasonable time entitles the affected person to commence proceedings against the manufacturer.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Section 272 sets out the basis upon which damages can be recovered from the manufacturer in such circumstances, while s 273 imposes a three year limitation period.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-200" bw.pnum="[315-200]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all">
	<title>Warranty provisions and compliance with Australian Consumer Law requirements</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Section 102(3) of the Australian Consumer Law (<emphasis type="bold">ACL</emphasis>) defines a “warranty against defects” as:</ptext>
	  <qpara>
	    <ptext>a representation communicated to a consumer in connection with the supply of goods or services, at or about the time of supply, to the effect that a person will (unconditionally or on specified conditions):</ptext>
	    <list before="(" after=")" type="lca">
	      <li>
		<ptext>repair or replace the goods or part of them; or</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>provide again or rectify the services or part of them; or</ptext>
	      </li>
<li>
		<ptext>wholly or partly recompense the consumer;</ptext>
	      </li>
</list>
<ptext>if the goods or services or part of them are defective, and includes any document by which such a representation is evidenced.</ptext>
	  </qpara>
</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Section 102(1) of the ACL provides that regulations may prescribe requirements relating to the form and contents of warranties against defects: see Competition and Consumer Regulations 2010 (Cth) reg 90(1)<annot id="PITS.IT.315-200.ANT1">
	      <label>1.</label>
	      <p>
		<ptext>Parts 6 and 7 of the Competition and Consumer Regulations 2010 (Cth) contain regulations made under the ACL, and may be referred to as the Australian Consumer Law Regulations.</ptext>
	      </p>
</annot>
 for a list of these requirements.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
</group>
<group>
      <title>Intellectual property rights in IT law</title>
      <para0 id="PITS.IT.315-205" bw.pnum="[315-205]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The supply of hardware and software will always involve a consideration of intellectual and industrial property rights associated with the product.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>This is not an issue unique to computer products. Nevertheless software supply agreements are likely to pay particular attention to ownership rights — the ownership of software is often contentious because of the manner in which one person's
original concept may subsequently be developed or modified by another or because parties to a joint development project have fallen out. The computer software industry seems particularly susceptible to claims of plagiarism.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext> For these reasons, a licensee of software is likely to seek an indemnity from the licensor in the event of a claim by a third party alleging breach of intellectual or industrial property rights. It is accordingly appropriate to examine in
this chapter the various rights that might give rise to such a claim.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-210" bw.pnum="[315-210]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Copyright</title>
	<para.grp>
	  <title>Copyright Act 1968 (Cth)</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>The <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="n">Copyright Act 1968 (Cth)</xref> was amended on 15 June 1984 in order to deal directly with the problems posed by computer programs.<annot id="PITS.IT.315-210.ANT1">
		<label>1.</label>
		<p>
		  <ptext>Prior to the amendment, the Act did not specifically address the question of whether copyright could subsist in software and this uncertainty increased following a judgment by the Federal Court of
Australia in <case.cit>
		      <lit>Apple Computer Inc v Computer Edge Pty Ltd</lit>
		      <cit year="1983" volume="50" series="ALR" pgnumber="581" vsprefid="50-ALR-581" link="n" yr.encl="parens">(1983) 50 ALR 581</cit>
		      <cit year="1983" volume="1" series="IPR" pgnumber="353" vsprefid="1983-1-IRP-353" link="y" yr.encl="parens">1 IPR 353</cit>
		    </case.cit>
 on 7 December 1983 to the effect that copyright did not subsist in a computer program. Ultimately, on appeal, the High Court of Australia held, by a 3:2
majority, that copyright subsisted in the source code but not in the object code of a computer program: <case.cit>
		      <lit>Computer Edge Pty Ltd v Apple Computer Inc</lit>
		      <cit year="1986" volume="161" series="CLR" pgnumber="171" vsprefid="161-CLR-171" link="n" yr.encl="parens">(1986) 161 CLR 171</cit>
		      <cit year="1986" volume="65" series="ALR" pgnumber="33" vsprefid="65-ALR-33" link="y" yr.encl="parens">65 ALR 33</cit>
		      <cit year="1986" volume="6" series="IPR" pgnumber="1" vsprefid="1986-6-IPR-1" link="y" yr.encl="parens">6 IPR 1</cit>
		      <u.cit mncit="BC8601422"> BC8601422</u.cit>
		    </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
		</p>
</annot>
</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>As a result of the 1984 amendments, <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S10" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="n">s 10</xref> of the Copyright Act was amended to include in the definition of a “literary work” a “computer
program or compilation of computer programs”.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>The Act was subject to further significant amendment, particularly by virtue of the <xref xrefid="OTH.CACPC99" leg-code="CACPC99" doc-code="OTH" link-to="leg" link="y">Copyright Amendment (Computer Programs) Act 1999</xref> (Cth) and the <xref xrefid="OTH.CADAAC00" leg-code="CADAAC00" doc-code="OTH" link-to="leg" link="y">Copyright Amendment (Digital Agenda) Act 2000</xref> (Cth).</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Further amendments were introduced in response to Australia's obligations under the Australia-US Free Trade Agreement. These changes were introduced by the US-Free Trade Agreement Implementation Act 2004 (Cth) and the Copyright Legislation
Amendment Act 2004 (Cth).</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext><xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47F.S10" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Section 10</xref> of the Act defines a “computer program” as a “set of statements or instructions to be used directly or indirectly in a computer in
order to bring about a certain result”.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>By virtue of <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S31.1.A.I" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">s 31(1)(a)(i)</xref> , the copyright owner has the exclusive right to reproduce the computer program in a “material form”. “Material
form” is defined, following amendment by the US-Free Trade Agreement Implementation Act 2004 (Cth), as “any form (whether visible or not) of storage of the work or adaptation, or a substantial part of the work or adaptation (whether or not the work
or adaptation, or a substantial part of the work or adaptation, can be reproduced)”.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Also of significance is s 31(1)(a)(iv) which provides the copyright owner with the exclusive right to communicate a work, including a computer program, to the public.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Section 21 expands upon the meaning of “reproduction”. In particular, <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S21.5" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">s 21(5)</xref> clarifies that the conversion of a computer program from one type
of code to another type of code amounts to a “reproduction”.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>Part III Div 4A of the Act lists a number of acts which are deemed not to constitute an infringement of copyright even though reproduction is involved. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47B.3" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Section
47B(3)</xref> permits reproduction if this is incidentally and automatically part of the technical process of running a copy of the program for the purpose of studying the ideas behind it. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47C" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Section 47C</xref> permits reproduction for the purpose of making a backup copy, subject to certain limitations. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47D" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Section 47D</xref> permits
the reproduction of a computer program for the purpose of obtaining information necessary to enable the licensee to make an interoperable product. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47E" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Section 47E</xref> permits
reproduction for the purpose of correcting errors in certain circumstances where the owner refuses to do so, and <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47F" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">s 47F</xref> authorises reproduction for the purposes
of security testing in similar circumstances. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47H" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Section 47H</xref> states that a contractual provision purporting to exclude or limit the operation of <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47B.3" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">s 47B(3)</xref> or <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47C" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">ss 47C</xref> , <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47D" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">47D</xref> , <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47E" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">47E</xref> or <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S47F" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IOCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">47F</xref> has no effect.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Moral rights</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>In contracts involving the creation of new materials (particularly software development, website development and multimedia development contracts), attention must be paid to the moral rights of the author. The protection of moral rights came
into force on 21 December 2000 with the enactment of the <xref xrefid="OTH.CAMRAC00" leg-code="CAMRAC00" doc-code="OTH" link-to="leg" link="y">Copyright Amendment (Moral Rights) Act 2000</xref> (Cth). The regime protects the authors’ rights of attribution
and integrity.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Particular intellectual property rights issues</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext><emphasis type="bold">New materials</emphasis> Generally, in relation to contracts for the creation of new materials, close consideration must be given to the question of ownership of intellectual property rights. Under s 35(1), ownership
will vest in the author (developer) unless the program is created in the course of the author's employment or unless there is an assignment in writing by the author to the commissioner. It is important, therefore, for software development contracts to
ensure that the customer is expressly assigned ownership of intellectual property if this is the intended outcome: see, for example, <case.cit>
		<lit>Cope Allman (Marrickville) Pty Ltd v Farrow</lit>
		<cit year="1984" volume="3" series="IPR" pgnumber="567" vsprefid="3-IPR-567" yr.encl="parens">(1984) 3 IPR 567</cit>
	      </case.cit>
; <case.cit>
		<lit>Avtex Airservices Pty Ltd v Bartsch</lit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="107" series="ALR" pgnumber="539" vsprefid="107-ALR-539" yr.encl="parens">(1992) 107 ALR 539</cit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="23" series="IPR" pgnumber="469" vsprefid="23-IPR-469" yr.encl="parens">23 IPR 469</cit>
	      </case.cit>
. One exception to this default position of ownership relates to Crown Copyright whereby, by virtue of<xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA.S176.8" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y"> s 176(2)</xref>, the government is, in the absence of express agreement to the contrary, deemed to be the owner of the copyright in an original work “made by, or under the directional control
of” the government.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext><emphasis type="bold">Hypertext links</emphasis> have given rise to copyright issues which will sometimes have to be addressed in IT contracts or website terms and conditions. It is generally accepted that the creation of a hyperlink will not
give rise to direct copyright infringement in the linked site: see <case.cit>
		<lit>Shetland Times Co Ltd v Wills</lit>
		<cit year="1997" series="SC" pgnumber="316" vsprefid="1997-SC-316" yr.encl="brackets">[1997] SC 316</cit>
	      </case.cit>
. Nevertheless a
website owner might be held liable for authorising infringement by providing a link to a site which itself is engaged in copyright infringing activities: <case.cit>
		<lit>Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd v Cooper</lit>
		<cit year="2005" volume="65" series="IPR" pgnumber="409" vsprefid="65-IPR-409" yr.encl="parens">(2005) 65 IPR 409</cit>
		<u.cit mncit="2005-FCA-972">[2005] FCA 972</u.cit>
		<u.cit jurisdiction="FC" bcnum="BC200505025">BC200505025</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
.</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext><emphasis type="bold">Multimedia products</emphasis> also give rise to unique copyright issues. There has been considerable debate in the past as to whether a multimedia product is protected under the Copyright Act as a “computer program” or
as a “cinematograph film”. The latter would appear to be the case where the product generates visual images shown as a moving picture, notwithstanding the fact that the display is not in the form of a conventional film: <case.cit>
		<lit>Galaxy Electronics
Pty Ltd v Sega Enterprises Ltd</lit>
		<cit year="1997" volume="75" series="FCR" pgnumber="8" vsprefid="75-FCR-8" yr.encl="parens">(1997) 75 FCR 8</cit>
		<cit year="1997" volume="145" series="ALR" pgnumber="21" vsprefid="145-ALR-21" yr.encl="parens">145 ALR
21</cit>
		<cit year="1997" volume="37" series="IPR" pgnumber="462" vsprefid="37-IPR-462" yr.encl="parens">37 IPR 462</cit>
		<u.cit bcnum="BC9702028">BC9702028</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
; <case.cit>
		<lit>Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment </lit>
		<cit volume="" pgnumber="" vsprefid="-">(2005) 221 ALR 448</cit>
		<cit volume="65" series="IPR" pgnumber="513" vsprefid="65-IPR-513">65 IPR 513</cit>
		<u.cit mncit="2005-HCA-58">[2005] HCA 58</u.cit>
		<u.cit jurisdiction="HC" bcnum="BC200507453">BC200507453</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
. A multimedia product is not, however, likely to be classified as a “dramatic work”: <case.cit>
		<lit>Pacific Gaming Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Leisure Industries Pty Ltd</lit>
		<cit year="2001" volume="116" series="FCR" pgnumber="448" vsprefid="116-FCR-448" yr.encl="parens">(2001) 116 FCR 448</cit>
		<u.cit mncit="2001-FCA-1636">[2001] FCA 1636</u.cit>
		<u.cit jurisdiction="FC" bcnum="BC200107323">BC200107323</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<p>
	  <ptext><emphasis type="bold">Circumvention devices</emphasis> Another copyright issue which may be of particular relevance to certain IT distribution contracts involves the use of circumvention devices. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Part V Div 2A</xref> of the Copyright Act provides a civil remedy in circumstances where a person circumvents or facilitates the circumvention of a “technological protection measure” or distributes,
imports or communicates any work in respect of which “electronic rights management information” has been removed or altered. “Electronic rights management information” is information identifying the copyright owner and prescribing
terms and conditions on which the work can be used; a “circumvention device” is a device designed for the purpose of circumventing a “technological protection measure”; a “technological protection measure” is a product
designed to prevent or inhibit the infringement of copyright. <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="y">Division 2A</xref> has proved to be of particular relevance to the global marketing of computer games, and
was the subject of consideration by the High Court of Australia in <case.cit>
	      <lit>Stevens v Kabushiki Kaisha Sony Computer Entertainment</lit>
	      <cit year="2005" volume="224" series="CLR" pgnumber="193" vsprefid="224-CLR-193" yr.encl="parens">(2005) 224
CLR 193</cit>
	      <cit year="2005" volume="221" series="ALR" pgnumber="448" vsprefid="221-ALR-448" yr.encl="parens">221 ALR 448</cit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2005-HCA-58">[2005] HCA 58</u.cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="HC" bcnum="BC200507453">BC200507453</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 in
which the court concluded that the appellant's mod chip was not a “circumvention device” because the access code incorporated by the respondent in its PlayStations did not constitute a “technological protection measure” as defined
by the legislation.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-215" bw.pnum="[315-215]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Patents</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>The <xref xrefid="OTH.PAT90" leg-code="PAT90" link-to="leg" link="n">Patents Act 1990 (Cth)</xref> does not deal specifically with software, although it is an established principle that an intangible product is patentable if it involves a process
which achieves a new and useful effect. Until 2013, there were no Australian court decisions on the patentability of software software (see <case.cit>
	      <lit>Research Affiliates LLC v Commissioner of Patents</lit>
	      <cit year="2013" volume="300" series="ALR" pgnumber="724" vsprefid="300-ALR-724" yr.encl="parens">(2013) 300 ALR 724</cit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2013-FCA-71">[2013] FCA 71</u.cit>
	      <u.cit jurisdiction="FC" bcnum="BC201300496">BC201300496</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
 and <case.cit>
	      <lit>RPL Central Pty Ltd
v Commissioner of Patents</lit>
	      <u.cit mncit="2013-FCA-871">[2013] FCA 871</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
; and the Australian Patent Office has consistently denied patentability on the grounds that computer programs per se are generally no more than methods
of calculating mathematical problems and are simply schemes or instructions on how to use a computer in a particular manner.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>There is a greater prospect of patents being granted in respect of computer related apparatuses or processes. In <case.cit>
	      <lit>International Business Machines Corp v Patents Cmr</lit>
	      <cit year="1991" volume="33" series="FCR" pgnumber="218" vsprefid="33-FCR-218" yr.encl="parens">(1991) 33 FCR 218</cit>
	      <cit year="1991" volume="405" series="ALR" pgnumber="388" vsprefid="405-ALR-388" yr.encl="parens">405 ALR 388</cit>
	      <cit year="1991" volume="22" series="IPR" pgnumber="417" vsprefid="22-IPR-417" yr.encl="parens">22 IPR 417</cit>
	    </case.cit>
; the Federal Court disagreed with the basis upon which the Commissioner of Patents had refused a patent for an invention involving an improved method and apparatus for representing curved images in computer
graphics displays. The commissioner had expressed the view that arithmetic computations which provide the basis for the representation of the curved images represented only a mathematical algorithm, not a “method of manufacture”. The court
remitted the application for reconsideration by the commissioner on the basis that the stated formula, when read in the context of the application as a whole, was one which related to the achievement of an end — the production of the improved curved
image — and that on this basis it was entitled to the protection of patent law.</ptext>
	</p>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,555" servnumber="272"?>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-220" bw.pnum="[315-220]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Confidential information</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A licensee's use of software may be interrupted by a claim by a third party that the use constitutes a breach of confidentiality. Where a computer program contains confidential information supplied by a third party, that third party may be
able to obtain a restraining order.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The difficulty would appear to lie, however, in establishing that the information in question has the necessary quality of confidentiality, which would certainly be lacking where (for example) a program has a large circulation.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-225" bw.pnum="[315-225]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Registered designs</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>It is possible to register a design under the <xref xrefid="OTH.DES" leg-code="DES" link-to="leg" link="n">Designs Act 2003 (Cth)</xref> (Designs Act) if it satisfies the two-step threshold test for a registrable design as set out in s 15(1).</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>For a design to be registrable, it must be new and distinctive when compared with the prior art base as it existed before the priority date of the design. Questions have previously arisen as to whether the pattern of circuitry on a semi-conductor
chip would be registrable under the Designs Act but for practical purposes the relevant protection would be sought under the Circuit Layouts Act 1989 (Cth) <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-240" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com">[315-240]</xref>.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-230" bw.pnum="[315-230]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Trade names and trade marks</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A limited form of proprietary interest in software may arise through the registration of a trade mark or trade name.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Trade marks are governed by the <xref xrefid="IPP.TMA.TM95" leg-code="TMA95" doc-code="IPP" link-to="leg" link="y">Trade Marks Act 1995 (Cth)</xref> and extend to such matters as logos, made-up names and names in a stylised form. Trade marks
may be registered but need not be registered in order to qualify for protection under the Act.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Trade names can be registered in accordance with legislation operating in each state and, while not conferring proprietary rights per se may enable the registrant to object to the registration of a similar name which might cause confusion.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-235" bw.pnum="[315-235]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<?Pub _bookmark Command="24 Feb 2006"?>
	<title>Passing off</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>A licensee may be restrained from using software if a third party can establish that the use of the software amounts to “passing off”. This cause of action may arise at common law as the “tort of passing off” or under <xref xrefid="OTH.TPA74.S51A" leg-code="TPA74" link-to="leg" link="n">ss 51A–65A</xref> of the Trade Practices Act 1974 (Cth). For example, if the licensee is a corporation and its use of the software amounts to “conduct that is misleading or deceptive
or is likely to mislead or deceive” on the basis that the third party's interest or input into the software is not acknowledged, then the licensee may be in breach of <xref xrefid="OTH.TPA74.S52" leg-code="TPA74" link-to="leg" link="n">s 52</xref> of
the Trade Practices Act.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-400" bw.pnum="[315-240]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Circuit Layouts Act 1989</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>Although not of immense relevance to computer contracts per se, the impact of the <xref xrefid="OTH.CLC89" leg-code="CLC89" link-to="leg" link="n">Circuit Layouts Act 1989 (Cth)</xref> (Circuit Layouts Act) on intellectual property rights which
would otherwise arise under the <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="n">Copyright Act 1968 (Cth)</xref> should be borne in mind.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The Circuit Layouts Act provides <emphasis>sui generis</emphasis> protection in Australia to integrated circuit layouts. The legislation was considered necessary because of doubt surrounding the extent of protection for circuit layouts conferred
by the Copyright Act 1968 (Cth) (Copyright Act). <case.cit>
	      <lit>Computer Edge Pty Ltd v Apple Computer Inc</lit>
	      <cit year="1986" volume="161" series="CLR" pgnumber="171" vsprefid="161-CLR-171" link="n" yr.encl="parens">(1986) 161 CLR 171</cit>
	      <cit year="1986" volume="65" series="ALR" pgnumber="33" vsprefid="65-ALR-33" link="y" yr.encl="parens">65 ALR 33</cit>
	      <cit year="1986" volume="6" series="IPR" pgnumber="1" vsprefid="1986-6-IPR-1" link="y" yr.encl="parens">6 IPR 1</cit>
	      <u.cit bcnum="BC8601422"> BC8601422</u.cit>
	    </case.cit>
; discussed above in <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-210" doc-code="PITS" link-to="com" link="y">[315-210]</xref> , dealt with piracy of semiconductors but did not address the question of whether copyright afforded protection to circuit
layouts as artistic works. Instead, it concentrated on the question of whether copyright existed in the computer programs stored in the semiconductors themselves.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>The Circuit Layouts Act confers monopoly rights on circuit layouts. These rights are known as “EL rights” (<xref xrefid="OTH.CLC89.S6" leg-code="CLC89" link-to="leg" link="n">s 6</xref>). Pursuant to <xref xrefid="OTH.CLC89.S17" leg-code="CLC89" link-to="leg" link="n">s 17</xref> , the owner of EL rights acquires the following exclusive rights:</ptext>
	  <list before="(" after=")" column="1" type="lca">
	    <li>
	      <ptext>to copy the layout, directly or indirectly, in a material form;</ptext>
	    </li>
<li>
	      <ptext>to make an integrated circuit in accordance with the layout or a copy of the layout;</ptext>
	    </li>
<li>
	      <ptext>to exploit the layout commercially in Australia.</ptext>
	    </li>
</list>
</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Infringement can occur (<xref xrefid="OTH.CLC89.S19" leg-code="CLC89" link-to="leg" link="n">s 19</xref>) as a result of unauthorised copying of the layout or unlicensed commercial exploitation. “Commercial exploitation” includes
(<xref xrefid="OTH.CLC89.S8" leg-code="CLC89" link-to="leg" link="n">s 8</xref>) sale, advertising for sale and importation for the purpose of sale.</ptext>
	</p>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Defences</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>The Circuit Layouts Act contains a number of defences and it is in this regard that differences between the operation of the Circuit Layouts Act and the Copyright Act emerge. Of particular relevance are the defences of copying for the purpose
of “genuine evaluation or analysis” (<xref xrefid="OTH.CPA.S23" leg-code="CPA" link-to="leg" link="n">s 23</xref> ) and unlicensed “first sales” in Australia (<xref xrefid="OTH.CPA.S24" leg-code="CPA" link-to="leg" link="n">s
24</xref> ).</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>In relation to the “evaluation or analysis” defence, EL rights are not infringed if, <wp language="latin" emphasis="roman">inter alia</wp> , a circuit layout is copied (or “reverse engineered”) for the purpose of “evaluating
or analysing” it. The rationale is that genuine evaluation or analysis for the purpose of creating a totally independent product of similar functionality is inoffensive. The section was considered in the case of <case.cit>
		<lit>Nintendo Co Ltd v
Centronics Systems Pty Ltd</lit>
		<cit year="1991" volume="23" series="IPR" pgnumber="119" vsprefid="23-IPR-119" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1991) 23 IPR 119</cit>
	      </case.cit>
 in which it was emphasised that the analysis must be intended to lead to the creation
of an independent design, as opposed to a simple copying or “shrinking” of the applicant's design “with no intellectual or unique design work being carried out”. The fact that the Act does permit, subject to the above qualification, “reverse
engineering” in appropriate circumstances forms an interesting contrast with <case.cit>
		<lit>Autodesk Inc v Dyason</lit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="173" series="CLR" pgnumber="330" vsprefid="173-CLR-330" link="n" yr.encl="parens">(1992) 173 CLR 330</cit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="104" series="ALR" pgnumber="563" vsprefid="104-ALR-563" link="y" yr.encl="parens">104 ALR 563</cit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="22" series="IPR" pgnumber="163" vsprefid="1992-104-IPR-163" link="y" yr.encl="parens">22 IPR 163</cit>
		<u.cit bcnum="BC9202706">BC9202706</u.cit>
	      </case.cit>
 in which the process of reverse engineering, to the extent it involved copying a substantial part of the applicant's code, amounted to an infringement of the <xref xrefid="OTH.CPA" leg-code="CPA" link-to="leg" link="n">Copyright Act</xref> regardless of the respondent's purpose in so doing. It should be noted that the <case.cit>
		<s.lit>Nintendo</s.lit>
		<pop.case.cit>
		  <lit>Nintendo Co Ltd v Centronics Systems Pty Ltd</lit>
		  <cit year="1991" volume="23" series="IPR" pgnumber="119" vsprefid="23-IPR-119" link="y" yr.encl="parens">(1991) 23 IPR 119</cit>
		</pop.case.cit>
</case.cit>
 decision was reversed on appeal, the Full Court of the Federal Court concentrating on the transitional implications
of <xref xrefid="OTH.CPA.S19.3" leg-code="CPA" link-to="leg" link="n">ss 19(3)</xref> and <xref xrefid="OTH.CPA.S20.1" leg-code="CPA" link-to="leg" link="n">20(1)</xref> : <case.cit>
		<lit>Centronics Systems Pty Ltd v Nintendo Co Ltd</lit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="39" series="FCR" pgnumber="147" vsprefid="1992-39-FCR-147" link="n" yr.encl="parens">(1992) 39 FCR 147</cit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="111" series="ALR" pgnumber="13" vsprefid="1992-111-ALR-13" link="y" yr.encl="parens">111 ALR 13</cit>
		<cit year="1992" volume="24" series="IPR" pgnumber="481" vsprefid="24-IPR-481" link="y" yr.encl="parens">24 IPR 481</cit>
	      </case.cit>
 .</ptext>
	  </p>
<p>
	    <ptext>In relation to the “first sale doctrine”, <xref xrefid="OTH.CPA.S24" leg-code="CPA" link-to="leg" link="n">s 24</xref> provides that, <wp language="latin" emphasis="ital">inter alia</wp> , it is not an infringement of EL rights
if a person acquires a layout direct from the manufacturer and then commercially exploits it, regardless of the existence of a licence to do so. <xref xrefid="OTH.CPA.S24.2" leg-code="CPA" link-to="leg" link="n">Section 24(2)</xref> provides, in effect,
that where such commercial exploitation would otherwise amount to “parallel importing” under the Copyright Act, no infringement of the Copyright Act will be deemed to have occurred. The operation of this provision was considered in <case.cit>
		<lit>Avel Pty Ltd v Wells</lit>
		<cit>(1991) 105 ALR 635</cit>
		<cit year="1991" volume="22" series="IPR" pgnumber="305" vsprefid="22-IPR-305" link="y" yr.encl="parens">22 IPR 305</cit>
	      </case.cit>
 in which the defence was successfully invoked. One consequence
of the decision is that computer programs stored in semiconductors may in appropriate circumstances be the subject of legitimate parallel importation, while computer programs stored by other means will be protected by the Copyright Act.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
<para.grp>
	  <title>Drafting considerations</title>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>These are all issues which affect the contents of software licences. Practitioners will have to consider, where relevant, the implications of clauses relating to reverse engineering, licensed importing, distribution and intellectual property
rights indemnities in the appropriate circumstances.</ptext>
	  </p>
</para.grp>
</para0>
</group>
<group>
      <title>Remedies for breach of IT contracts</title>
      <para0 id="PITS.IT.315-245" bw.pnum="[315-245]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>There are no remedies for breach of contract which are confined to the realm of computer transactions. However, it is worth noting some of the more common remedies employed when disputes arise.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-250" bw.pnum="[315-250]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Damages</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>In the absence of an appropriate limitation of liability clause, an aggrieved party can sue for damages for breach of contract. This is a relatively uncomplicated process when damages are liquidated whereas the ultimate quantification of unliquidated
claims can be more complicated. It will be the court's task to place the plaintiff in the same position as it would have been were it not for the defendant's breach. It is probably not appropriate to explore the nature of such damages further in this
chapter.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Damages can also be sought for infringement of intellectual property rights. This constitutes a separate cause of action. The quantification of damages will still be made on general principles apart from the fact that the <xref xrefid="IPCPY.CPA.CPA" leg-code="CPA" doc-code="IPCPY" link-to="leg" link="n">Copyright Act 1968 (Cth)</xref> allows the court to additionally take into account such matters as the flagrancy of the infringement, the benefits shown to have accrued to
the defendant and “all other relevant matters”. The Copyright Act also makes provision for conversion damages in addition to general damages.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Another common cause of action for damages in respect of the breach of an IT contract arises under Pt 2.1 of the Australian Consumer Law (<emphasis type="bold">ACL</emphasis>).  Section 18 of the ACL prohibits false or misleading
conduct and is often invoked against suppliers which might otherwise have the benefit of a cap on their contractual liability for damages. Liability under Pt 2.1 of the ACL cannot be capped.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-255" bw.pnum="[315-255]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Anton Piller orders</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>An <emphasis type="ital" shading="nil">Anton Piller</emphasis> order is frequently used as a weapon against breach of copyright in software. This remedy enables a plaintiff to enter the defendant's premises, search for the infringing article
and to remove it for the purpose of preservation and inspection pending trial or subsequent court application: <case.cit>
	      <lit>Anton Piller KG v Manufacturing Process Ltd</lit>
	      <cit year="1976" volume="1" series="AllER" pgnumber="779" vsprefid="1976-1-AllER-779" yr.encl="brackets">[1976] 1 All ER 779</cit>
	    </case.cit>
.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext><emphasis type="ital" shading="nil">Anton Piller</emphasis> orders are frequently used as remedies against piracy of computer products and as such may, on occasion, interrupt the contractual relationship between a licensor and a licensee.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
<para0 id="PITS.IT.315-260" bw.pnum="[315-260]" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" icon="none" annotloc="para0">
	<title>Injunctions</title>
	<p>
	  <ptext>An injunction may be used to restrain a defendant from doing a specified act and is an important form of relief in protecting software which may have a limited commercial life and in respect of which a subsequent award of damages will be totally
inadequate.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>An injunction is an equitable remedy which will only be granted when a plaintiff can show it has a prima facie case or, at least, a strong probability of success at trial. It will also be necessary to establish that the balance of convenience
favours the grant of injunctive relief.</ptext>
	</p>
<p>
	  <ptext>Again, the significance of this remedy to IT contracts is that it may interrupt the relationship between a licensor and licensee, in particular, and the licence agreement should therefore address the question of the rights of the respective
parties in the event of such an occurrence.</ptext>
	</p>
</para0>
</group>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,595" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
</comm.chap>
<?Pub CX edit5(guidecard(title()gc.front()?>
  <prec.grp id="PITS.IT-prec.grp_1">
    <title>Precedents to Information Technology</title>
    <prec id="PITS.IT.P315-1" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.1</label>
      <title>Software licence<annot id="PITS.IT.P315-1.ANT1">
	  <label>1</label>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>See commentary at <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-50" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com">[315-50]</xref>.</ptext>
	  </p>
</annot>
</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, a supplier who owns software grants a licence to a customer to use that software under the conditions set out in the agreement. The licence is a non-transferrable,
non-exclusive, perpetual licence. The supplier retains ownership of the software. The customer must only use the software on particular equipment and the usual restrictions on use apply (no copying the software, no modifying the software etc). The supplier
is not required to install the software or provide updates. The supplier is not required to provide any support services.</emphasis>:</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>This precedent attempts to strike a balance between the interests of the supplier and the those of the customer. More often than not, licences are drafted with a supplier bias
because it is the supplier who prepares the document initially, and because suppliers have an understandable interest in maintaining consistent terms for the licensing of their product throughout the marketplace. Depending on the influence of the Customer,
however, modifications are often negotiated. This precedent is intended to take a form which should address the legitimate expectations of both parties.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Software licences can take many forms. This precedent represents the most common form of licence. There are other types of standard form software licences which, by their nature,
are non-negotiable, such as webwrap, shrinkwrap and clickwrap licences. There are also licences which are tailored for a more specific purpose than to simply grant the customer commercial rights of use — for example, beta testing agreements (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-3" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.3</xref>) which involve the trialing of software still under development; evaluation agreements (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-4" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.4</xref>) which
provide the customer with temporary use rights; and multi-facility agreements (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-2" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.2</xref>) which contemplate the rollout of a software product on an optional basis at multiple customer
sites. The possible variations are endless. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>While the precedent below attempts to address the legitimate interests of both parties, there will nevertheless be some clauses more open to negotiation than others. Examples
include acceptance (suppliers will seek to minimise the implications of acceptance failure while customers will seek to ensure that acceptance failure is grounds for immediate termination), escrow (some suppliers are resistant to placing a copy of their
source code into escrow, particularly if the product is in mass circulation) and liability (suppliers will invariably seek to exclude all liability for indirect loss, and sometimes also for most forms of direct loss, whereas customers will prefer a liability
cap representing a multiple of the licence fee).</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-1.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-1.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,611" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-2" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.2</label>
      <title>Multi-facility software licence<annot id="PITS.IT.P315-2.ANT1">
	  <label>1</label>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>See commentary at <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-50" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com">[315-50]</xref>.</ptext>
	  </p>
</annot>
</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>A multi-facility software licence is used where a customer operates its business at various sites (or branches) and wishes to use the supplier’s software at each branch,
although the specifications may be different for each branch. The branch will issue a purchase order for the software including specifications for that branch, and the supplier will supply software to that branch. In the case of each branch the software
is supplied under the terms of this master licence agreement. The supplier will install the software at the branches but is not required to provide any support services. The supplier retains ownership of the software. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>This precedent attempts to strike a balance between the interests of the supplier and the customer. More often than not, licences are drafted with a supplier bias because it
is the supplier who prepares the document initially, and because suppliers have an understandable interest in maintaining consistent terms for the licensing of their product throughout the marketplace. Depending on the influence of the customer, however,
modifications are often negotiated. This precedent is intended to take a form which should address the legitimate expectations of both parties.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Software licences can take many forms. This precedent is based on a standard software licence but with a particular focus, being the optional rollout to different sites within
an organisation and the segregation and balancing of rights and obligations as between the parties in respect of individual branches on the one hand, and the overall licensing and rollout of the software on the other.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>While the precedent below attempts to provide a balanced approach which reflects the legitimate expectations of both parties, some clauses are more likely than others to be
the subject of possible negotiation. In a standard software licence, it can generally be expected that acceptance, escrow and liability provisions may be the subject of negotiations between the parties (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-1" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.1</xref>). In a multi-facility software licence, there is likely to be focused discussion on branch rights, including the question of whether an individual branch has the right to reject the product following acceptance testing
(even though it has passed acceptance testing at other venues) and whether a major failure of the software at one branch only has consequences in the context of that branch or whether it gives the customer a right to terminate the roll out as a whole.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="11" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-2.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="11" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-2.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,631" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-3" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.3</label>
      <title>Beta testing agreement<annot id="PITS.IT.P315-3.ANT1">
	  <label>1</label>
	  <p>
	    <ptext>See commentary at <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-80" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com">[315-80]</xref>.</ptext>
	  </p>
</annot>
</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, a supplier who owns software grants a customer a limited licence to test the software on a trial and evaluation basis. The customer must provide the
supplier with the results of the testing. The customer may, but need not, buy the software once it is commercially released.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>A beta testing agreement is a form of trialing agreement. Trialing can take a number of forms and might involve, for example, a third party expert which simply tests the product
under normal operating conditions. This precedent, however, contemplates the involvement of a regular user who is prepared to trial the software, typically on the basis that by providing feedback it can ensure that the end result is suitable to its requirements.
In these situations, the customer would generally expect some form of discount in return for its feedback. Shareware agreements (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-80" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com">[315-80]</xref>) are a less structured form of trial agreement
whereby the licensor takes advantage of any feedback which may be received from the user base.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>From a customer's perspective, the most important consideration will be to ensure that it is under no obligation to acquire a subsequent commercial release of the product if
it does not wish to. From the licensor's perspective, the most important requirement is that the customer provides constructive and structured feedback. The nature and extent of the latter obligation is quite often the subject of negotiation.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-3.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-3.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,651" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-4" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.4</label>
      <title>Software evaluation agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, a customer is granted permission to test software provided by the supplier. The evaluation agreement envisaged below differs from a beta testing agreement
(see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-3" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.3</xref>) in that while a beta testing agreement typically involves a product under development, a software evaluation agreement contemplates the trialing of an established
package.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The object of a software evaluation agreement is to provide the licensee with access to the software on an interim basis as an inducement for the customer to enter into a longer
term licence.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>The precedent below attempts to address the interests of both parties in a balanced manner. Ultimately, the final form of the agreement will be somewhat dependent on the relative
negotiating strengths of the parties. Clauses which will typically be the subject of negotiation between the parties include the extent of the customer's obligation to acquire the software at the end of the evaluation period; the extent of the supplier's
warranties and indemnities in circumstances where the customer has not made a commitment to the product; and the question of whether the source code should be placed in escrow given that the customer is yet to make a long-term commitment to the product.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-4.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-4.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,671" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-5" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.5</label>
      <title>Software support agreements</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the licensor of a software product agrees to provide support services. Support may alternatively be provided by an authorised third party but for convenience,
this precedent assumes that the licensor and the support service provider are one and the same entity. Support (or “maintenance”) services can embrace a range of activities which may or may not extend to the provision of updates and new releases, the
operation of a help desk, problem solving, operational advice, online fixes, on-site remediation and a range of documentation services.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>It follows that the definition of support (or “maintenance”) services is fundamental to the customer but it may nevertheless not be a clause open to negotiation —
the licensor will choose to offer whatever services it wishes to as part of its support offering, and the adequacy of these services will typically be a matter for the customer to consider when determining whether or not to acquire the product in the
first place.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Equally, it is important for customers to familiarise themselves with support “exclusions” so that there is no doubt as to what assistance is the subject of prepaid support
and what assistance is either not offered or requires an additional payment.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-5.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-5.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-10" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.10</label>
      <title>Software development agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the supplier agrees to develop a new software product for the customer. The agreement is most commonly used where a business has a unique requirement
which is not met by commercially available products. Agreements of this nature might also be used to effect major modifications to an existing proprietary product or a product already in use in the customer's business.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>A key issue for negotiation will be ownership of the finished product. In the absence of agreement to the contrary, copyright will be owned by the developer, a consequence
often not intended by customers and overlooked in contract deliberations. Alternatively, the parties may agree that the supplier will retain ownership of intellectual property rights and will license the developed product to the customer. This precedent
assumes that ownership vests in the customer.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Another important provision relates to development milestones. It is important for a customer to avoid a situation whereby it has an open-ended commitment to maintain the engagement
with the supplier, particularly in circumstances where the developed product is required within a defined timeframe.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Most customers will also seek a fixed price. Software development on a time-and-materials basis can prove costly for customers, more so if there is an absence of agreed milestones.
 Ideally from a customer's perspective, the fixed price will be payable in installments at the completion of specified milestone events.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-10.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-10.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,711" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-15" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.15</label>
      <title>Escrow agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the source code of the licensed software is placed in escrow with a third party, as a way of providing security (refer to the commentary at <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.315-90" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="com">[315-90]</xref>). </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The object of the agreement is to ensure that in the event that the licensor of the software becomes insolvent or for some other reason refuses or is unable to support the
product, the licensee can have access to the source code and, either itself or through a third party, ensure that the software is maintained in a useable state. Escrow agreements are not ideal for all scenarios. Global suppliers of major products are
unlikely to grant escrow to an individual customer; also, in some situations escrow will be impractical if no third party could be expected to possess the requisite skills to use the source code.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The principal issue for negotiation in any instance will be the triggering events — that is, the circumstances in which the source code will be released by the escrow
agent to the customer. Obviously the licensor will seek to limit the circumstances in which this may occur, whilst the customer will seek broader rights. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>The other important provision relates to verification — the customer needs to ensure that an independent third party (or the escrow agent itself if it possesses the requisite
skills) is able to access the source code periodically in order to determine that the escrow agent is holding the current and/or correct version of the product.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="7" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-15.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="7" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-15.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-20" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.20</label>
      <title>Equipment purchase agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>This agreement is used where there is a sale and purchase of hardware equipment.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>It is increasingly common for these types of agreements to be in a standard format, issued by the supplier, with a consequent restriction on the ability of the customer to
engage in realistic negotiations. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Nevertheless there will be situations in which a customer has sufficient bargaining power to negotiate the terms and ensure that the agreement is at least even-handed. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Where a customer has the ability to negotiate, the clauses most likely to be the subject of discussion between the parties will involve the extent of the customer's responsibility
to prepare the site; milestone dates for delivery; and (if relevant) installation, the nature of any acceptance testing to be carried out on the equipment prior to final payment, the extent of supplier warranties and the extent to which the supplier
seeks to exclude or cap its liability.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-20.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-20.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,751" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-25" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.25</label>
      <title>Equipment maintenance agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>This agreement is used in circumstances where a customer engages a service provider to provide maintenance for installed IT equipment.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The service provider in these circumstances may be a related corporation of the manufacturer or it may be an authorised third party. The precedent is appropriate in either
circumstance — the equipment sale agreement will be a separate contract.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Hardware maintenance services may come in a variety of forms but the two essential types of service are preventive maintenance (designed to avoid problems arising) and remedial
maintenance (designed to rectify problems which have occurred). Other types of maintenance activity might involve training, the provision of a help desk and the implementation of enhancements. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>The key issues for negotiation will involve the extent of the “in-scope” services; the extent of the “excluded” services and, related to these categorisations; the extent to
which the supplier has the right to make an additional charge for services which are regarded as falling outside the prepaid activities.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-25.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-25.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-30" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.30</label>
      <title>Systems integration agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the supplier agrees to provide the customer with an entire computer system, comprising both hardware and software. The supplier may be a specialist systems
integrator. Alternatively, the supplier may be the equipment manufacturer which has obtained the software from the third party, or a software supplier which has obtained the equipment from a third party. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The advantage to the customer is “one-stop shopping”. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Key issues for negotiation include the specifications clause (which is important because it identifies precisely the components to be supplied), the bundled payment clause
and the system acceptance clause (the latter being particularly significant because it is essential to show that not only do the hardware and the software comply with the specifications, but also that they work in combination according to the agreed
requirements.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-30.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-30.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-32" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.32</label>
      <title>Software integration agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the supplier (typically, the proprietor of software) agrees to integrate its software with third party software in order to form a working solution for
the customer. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Conceptually, the agreement is similar to a systems integration agreement, the difference being that whereas a systems integration agreement contemplates a combination of hardware
and software, a software integration agreement contemplates a combination of different software products only. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Typically, clauses which will come under scrutiny during negotiation include the terms of any third party licenses, the authority of the integrator to access, install and modify
a third party's software, milestone dates and milestone payments and the supplier's overall warranty that the various software components will work together so as to meet the customer's expectations.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="16" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-32.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="16" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-32.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,811" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-35" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.35</label>
      <title>Service bureau agreement (batch services)</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the service provider agrees to process the customer's data off-site, followed by physical delivery of the output to the customer's premises. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Agreements of this nature are now quite rare (but not non-existent) as there are more efficient ways of delivering a service online. More common off-site agreements of this
nature are reflected below in the precedents for an Application service provider agreement (see <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-42" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.42</xref>) and a general outsourcing agreement (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-73" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.73</xref>). </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Where a batch agreement is utilised, terms most likely to be the subject of negotiation will invariably relate to the quality of the output data, the nature of the service
provider's security and backup capability and the consequences (often in the form of service credits) for system failure and downtime.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-35.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-35.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-40" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.40</label>
      <title>Service bureau agreement (online
services)</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, a customer utilises the service provider's external computer facilities online for its internal data processing purposes. This type of agreement has
largely been superseded by Application Service Provider agreements and other outsourcing arrangements but it nevertheless retains some relevance.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The precedent below can be useful as a general template for new and emerging online data processing.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Issues which are most likely to be the subject of negotiation will include the extent of the customer's responsibility to provide its own access facilities; the extent of the
service provider's commitment to accuracy; the extent to which the customer can gain access to its data on an ongoing basis; and the consequences of system failure.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-40.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-40.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,851" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-42" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.42</label>
      <title>Application service provider agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the customer is granted access online to the supplier's software on a real-time basis, with charges determined by reference to the extent of the customer's
usage of the service.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The responsibility rests with the supplier to operate and maintain the servers which support the software. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>The advantage to the customer is that it is able to avoid investment in acquiring a system for itself, while direct costs are defrayed by the supplier's ability to spread use
over multiple clients. The software system is kept up to date and is often regarded as a more reliable and efficient than a system maintained in-house.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-42.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-42.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,871" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-45" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" pslinclude="INH" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.45</label>
      <title>Consultancy agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the consultant agrees to provide IT-related services to the customer. This precedent is of a generic nature and is designed for adaptation to any unique
situation involving the physical delivery of services, which might range from programming to evaluation to system analysis. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Similar but more specific agreements of this nature may take the form of enterprise architecture analysis agreements (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-74" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.74</xref>), gap analysis agreements (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-75" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.75</xref>), scoping agreements (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-77" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.77</xref>) and penetration
testing agreements (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-79" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.79</xref>).</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>This template in its generic form will prove to be relatively simple to negotiate. It is likely that the schedules describing services and addressing issues such as feels and
liability will be the more complex aspects of negotiation.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-45.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-45.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-50" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.50</label>
      <title>Disaster backup agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, two entities with substantial and compatible computer systems agree to provide a backup facility for each other.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Disaster backup agreements can take many forms. Sometimes an entity will enter into a contract for backup services with a third party specialist; and in many instances, an
entity will run its own backup system off-site. This precedent, however, deals with a third approach involving cooperation between two entities — in some instances, these entities may be related bodies corporate, but this does not have to be the
case. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Being an agreement for reciprocal services, the agreement is drafted from an even-handed perspective. This is not to say, however, that the negotiation of such an agreement
will necessarily be free from contention. Parties may have strong or differing views regarding the quality of the backup service the other is capable of offering, the notification process in the event that backup services are required, the identity of
personnel who might be required to assist with the backup service, the circumstances in which a party may execute a dry run of its backup plans, the extent of access to the backed-up system and the extent of each party's liability to the other in the
event of an inability to provide the service.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="12" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-50.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="12" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-50.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,911" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-55" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.55</label>
      <title>Deed of guarantee of performance</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this deed, two or more entities guarantee the performance by a supplier of services which it has separately contracted to provide to a customer.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Performance deeds may take many forms. Most commonly, a guarantee of this nature is provided by a related body corporate, normally the parent company, of the supplier. Sometimes
(as in the example in the template below), however, individuals (usually directors of the supplier) personally enter into the guarantee.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Under this template, two or more directors personally guarantee that the supplier will meet its obligations under the agreement. They undertake to indemnify the customer against
all loss arising out of the supplier’s failure to perform. Their liability is joint and several.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Directors are naturally reluctant to enter into agreements of this nature and typically would only agree to do so where they control a startup company with limited assets or
a company which is otherwise in a financially precarious position.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="2" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-55.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="2" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-55.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-60" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.60</label>
      <title>Employee’s deed of confidentiality</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this deed, an employee undertakes to the employer to preserve the confidentiality of certain information to which the employee is entrusted.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Agreements of this nature are redundant in some contexts. It will be an express or implied term of the employee's employment contract to maintain the confidentiality of the
employer's information and, regardless of any contractual obligation, the employee will be under an equitable obligation of confidence in relation to maintaining the secrecy of such information. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Nevertheless, customers dealing with an IT company commonly require evidence of the existence of a confidentiality deed between the supplier and its employees, and this provides
some measure of confidence that customer data entrusted to the supplier will be handled discretely.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="2" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-60.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="2" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-60.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-65" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.65</label>
      <title>Facilities management agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, a company which owns its own computer system engages another party (the supplier) to manage the system on its behalf. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>A facilities management agreement is a form of outsourcing, to the extent that the customer engages an outsider to manage its IT infrastructure. It differs from other types
of outsourcing agreements — such as application service provider agreements or general IT outsourcing agreements — in that other forms of outsourcing contemplate the supplier owning the technological infrastructure. Under a facilities management
scenario, the customer owns the infrastructure.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The critical aspect of a facilities management agreement involves service levels, that is, the minimum level of performance which the supplier must achieve in operating the
customers system, and the consequences of a failure to meet those service levels. This is more complicated than many other service level arrangements, however, because the supplier is operating a system which has been provided to it by the customer,
rather than a system which it has developed and implemented itself. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Another key issue involves third party software — the customer will have entered into a variety of software licenses relevant to its own requirements but such licences
may not necessarily permit a third party to have access to the program. Prior to entering the agreement, therefore, it is important for the parties to complete adequate due diligence to ensure that the supplier's involvement will not cause the customer
to be in breach of its contractual obligations to any third parties.</emphasis>] </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-65.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-65.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,931" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-70" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.70</label>
      <title>Customer order form for services and software licence</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this arrangement, a master agreement exists between the parties for the procurement of IT products and services. The customer can place an order in a prescribed form,
and follow a prescribed process, in order to acquire a volume of licences from the Supplier. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The customer also has the option to acquire “services” which typically would involve software support and related helpdesk services.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>The supply of the software is accompanied by standard licence terms. Typically, these terms will not be negotiable as they will have been pre-agreed as part of the master arrangement.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="6" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-70.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="6" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-70.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,951" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-73" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.73</label>
      <title>Outsourcing agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>This template is a generic outsourcing agreement which can be used in a variety of situations, most commonly for external processing services.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>In essence, this template contemplates a situation in which the customer is winding down its in-house computing operations and converting to an external service arrangement.
 It will sell its key IT infrastructure to the service provider, transfer existing licences and related service agreements and it may also negotiate the transfer or secondment of key staff.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Not all outsourcing agreements incorporate such radical upheaval. The sale of assets and the transfer of personnel, in particular, do not always occur, but in extreme instances
they may.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The provision of services will rest on compliance by the supplier with service levels. The customer may seek to incorporate a benchmarking clause in order to ensure that it
continues to obtain value for money throughout the term of the agreement.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>In contemplation of the ultimate termination of the arrangement, agreements of this nature should always include transition out provisions which enable a structured transfer
or reversion process to take place when the time comes.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="11" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-73.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="11" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-73.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="12,971" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-74" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.74</label>
      <title>Call centre services agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, which is a form of outsourcing, the supplier provides a solution to assist the customer with telephone call load management.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Agreements of this nature focus on a comprehensive description of the services and accompanying service levels. The description of the services embraces the service provider's
system and software platform, the customer's software and any specific function or business activities to which the calls will relate; the latter affecting the extent of customer information and training that will have to be provided to the service provider.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Service levels focus not only on the requisite responsiveness of the service providers staff but also on such matters such as staff levels, anticipated call volumes and average
handling times.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The service provider is likely to stipulate certain customer requirements which are regarded as essential for the efficient provision of the services, such as regular customer
forecasts as to volume activity and patterns.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>It is important to ensure that there is an obligation on the service provider to comply with the Do Not Call Register Act so as to avoid telemarketing calls to numbers which
are entered on the register.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-74.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-74.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-75" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.75</label>
      <title>Gap analysis agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the supplier agrees to conduct an assessment of the discrepancy between the customer's requirements as set out in its request for tender and the functionality
by a preferred tenderer in its response.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The gap analysis might be carried out by the preferred tenderer or by an independent third party. The significance of the discrepancy is assessed in order to determine whether
the customer's requirements can be satisfied by the tenderer's proposal or, alternatively, whether additional functionality must be provided either by the preferred tenderer or a third party.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Negotiations will typically focus on the central “business requirements definition”, together with timeframe for completion of the services and the format of the supplier's
report.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-75.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-75.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-76" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.76</label>
      <title>Implementation planning study
agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the supplier agrees to conduct a study of a proposed IT rollout in order to determine the extent of the likely complexities and the impact these complexities
may have on the ability of the supplier to satisfy the customer's requirements.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The project may be carried out by the ultimate service provider or by an independent third party. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>In other words, an implementation planning study agreement involves planning for an anticipated implementation that is particularly suited where an enterprise rollout which
may require some degree of flexibility as to both timing and location of services is involved.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-76.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-76.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-77" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.77</label>
      <title>Scoping agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, which is a form of consultancy agreement, the parties engage in a preliminary scoping exercise prior to the commencement of a major project.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Typically, the agreement will be used in circumstances where the customer has been unable to accurately or adequately specify its requirements and requires a detailed technical
investigation and deliberation for this purpose by the proposed supplier.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>The supplier will generally be required to produce deliverables in the form of technical specifications, time estimates and/or precise costings.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-77.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-77.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="13,051" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-78" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.78</label>
      <title>System access agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the owner of an IT facility permits another entity to utilise the facility for its own, specified purpose.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Negotiation will typically include the duration and timing of access, the purpose of the access, and the identity and number of individuals who are authorised to have access.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>There will generally be negotiations about what constitutes an “authorised use” of the system, with the owner being particularly concerned to ensure the accessing party undertakes
not to utilise the system for illegal purposes and that it agrees to refrain from any unauthorised modifications.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-78.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="8" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-78.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-79" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.79</label>
      <title>Penetration testing agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>A Penetration Testing Agreement permits an authorised user (the service provider) to have access to the customer's system for the specific objective of enabling the service
provider to identify any security short-comings which might otherwise enable an unauthorised third party to hack into the customer's system. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The agreement will give focus to the type or extent of testing which is to be conducted. Typically this would involve both “blind testing” (with the consultant relying only
on publicly available materials and resources) and “guided testing” (whereby the consultant is provided with certain background information of a nature which an “inside hacker” might possess).</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Invariably, the service provider will insist on including a disclaimer in respect of any disruption which the testing might cause to the customer's system, together with an
indemnity in relation to any intellectual property or confidentiality breaches which may be a byproduct of the testing process.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="13" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-79.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="13" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-79.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="13,091" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-80" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.80</label>
      <title>Panel agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, a supplier of IT goods or services is appointed to a panel of prequalified suppliers with whom the customer can elect to place orders from time to time.
 Arrangements of this nature are common in government and in large corporations. The advantage to the customer is that once the supplier has been approved for inclusion on the panel, it is no longer necessary to undertake a tendering process when it
requires goods or services of the nature which the supplier offers.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>It does not follow, however, that any element of competition necessarily disappears once a supplier is appointed. Suppliers will regularly be asked to quote against other panel
members who supply similar products or services, and the customer will determine which offer represents best value for money. The process is nevertheless far simpler than a full, formal, tender process. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>Generally it will be for the customer to stipulate the terms of appointment and the ordering process. There is typically little room for negotiation on these issues.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Beyond that, the terms (and hence the nature of any contract negotiations) will be governed by the nature of the goods or services which the supplier offers. To this extent,
it is appropriate to simply refer to the relevant template. Hence, for example, if the panel involves suppliers of computer equipment, the appropriate terms relevant to the sale of the equipment can be borrowed from <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-20" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.20</xref>.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="3" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-80.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="3" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-80.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="13,101" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-85" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.85</label>
      <title>Term agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, a customer appoints a supplier to provide specified IT requirements over an agreed period of time. The agreement differs from a panel arrangement (<xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-80" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.80</xref>) in that a panel arrangement contemplates a number of competing suppliers being appointed for a fixed term. Under this template, a sole supplier is appointed.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>The principal issue for negotiation will be the extent of the customer's right to purchase goods or services off the panel. The supplier's concern will be that while it will
be prepared to discount its fees in order to derive the benefits of a long-term commitment, this arrangement maybe undermined if the customer retains the right to circumvent the panel.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Beyond that, the terms (and hence the nature of any contract negotiations) will be governed by the nature of the goods or services which the supplier offers. To this extent,
it is appropriate to simply refer back to the relevant template. Hence, for example, if the arrangement involves a supplier of computer equipment, the appropriate terms relevant to the sale of the equipment can be borrowed from <xref xrefid="PITS.IT.P315-20" doc-code="AEFP" link-to="oth">Pr 315.20</xref>).</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="4" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-85.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="4" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-85.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-90" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.90</label>
      <title>Internet service provider agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, which for the most part will be non-negotiable, the internet service provider (ISP) specifies the means by which internet access will be made available
to the customer, the circumstances under which access might be withheld and the extent of the ISP's responsibility and liability for access difficulties experienced by the customer.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>The customer will generally be required to undertake to refrain from using the service for unlawful purposes including the dissemination of infringing, defamatory or offensive
material. Typically, an ISP agreement will incorporate, directly or by reference, an “acceptable use policy” to this effect.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="7" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-90.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="7" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-90.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="13,131" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-95" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" pslinclude="CON" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.95</label>
      <title>Website development and maintenance agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the supplier agrees to provide programming and related skills involved in the creation of a website, and thereafter to provide updating and general maintenance
services.</emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>A key issue for negotiation and agreement will be the development specifications and the agreement should make clear the extent to which the developer is entitled to exercise
creative discretion. It will also be necessary for the developer to specify precisely what data and other material it requires from the customer in order to complete the development.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>There also tends to be negotiation over liability and indemnity. The customer will be concerned to ensure that the developer does not introduce plagiarised software, content
or other design features while, at the same time, the supplier will require reassurance that content which the customer asks it to incorporate is itself non-infringing of a third party's rights. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Support services may cover a range of activities, depending in part on the extent of the customer's expertise. Possible issues for inclusion under “support services” might
include bug fixing, the creation of new features, the tabling of new ideas and concepts and the introduction of new technology.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-95.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="10" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-95.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="13,151" servnumber="272" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-100" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.100</label>
      <title>Teaming agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the two parties agree to cooperate in submitting a proposal to a customer which has issued a request for tender. Effectively, one party agrees to be
the contracting party and the other agrees to be the subcontracting party in the event the joint tender is successful. Typically, the contracting party will be the one which has the greater stake in the bid, whilst the subcontracting party will be providing
a smaller, yet critical, component of the goods or services being offered. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>One important issue to be addressed in negotiations will be the question of whether the teaming arrangement is exclusive or non exclusive — in other words, whether either
of the tendering parties is free to form an alliance with another bidder or alternatively to bid in its own name if it wishes. </emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>While the template below contemplates a specific project which is the subject of the teaming arrangement, other teaming agreements might involve a broader form of alliance,
whereby the parties agree to explore the possibility of collaborating in a range of future, as yet unspecified, tenders. In such circumstances, it is necessary to determine the term of such an arrangement and the geographic area to which it applies.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="7" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-100.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="7" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="center" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-100.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?pgbrk?>
<prec id="PITS.IT.P315-105" currmonth="oct" curryear="2013" currinclude="all" prec-author="G Hughes LLB (Hons) LLM (Melb) PhD (Mon)" currdate="201310" currtype="review" prectype="prec-doc">
      <label>315.105</label>
      <title>Multimedia development agreement</title>
      <repro-tx boxed="n" pointsize="10" shading="none">
	<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>[<emphasis>Under this agreement, the supplier agrees to develop a multimedia product for the customer. </emphasis></rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text>
	    <emphasis>In many respects, the issues are the same as apply under a software development agreement. The distinguishing feature of a multimedia development project, however, is that
intellectual property issues are generally more complex. Typically, a broad range of third party works will be incorporated into the end product, including software, text, photographs, films, sound recordings and designs.</emphasis>
	  </rx.text>
	</rx.p>
<rx.p line-spacing="single" emphasis="none" justify="full">
	  <rx.text><emphasis>Accordingly, negotiations in respect of agreements of this nature tend to focus on responsibility for procuring third party consent, together with the nature and extent of
indemnities for any intellectual property infringements.</emphasis>]</rx.text>
	</rx.p>
</repro-tx>
      <p>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="true" include="onlinecd" src="v07-315-105.doc"/>
	<graphic pages="9" orient="portrait" valign="middle" halign="left" externalfile="false" include="all" src="v07-315-105.doc"/>
      </p>
    </prec>
<?fascicle nextpg="14,001" servnumber="233" startpg="no" textcont="false"?>
</prec.grp>
</guidecard>